<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great commandment A discourse upon Psal. 73. 25. shewing that God is all things to a religious soul. Being a further explication of a short discourse called, The angelical life, formerly written by the same author S.S.</title>
            <author>Shaw, Samuel, 1635-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3036B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222383</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833562</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833562</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38039</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59600)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38039)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2217:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great commandment A discourse upon Psal. 73. 25. shewing that God is all things to a religious soul. Being a further explication of a short discourse called, The angelical life, formerly written by the same author S.S.</title>
                  <author>Shaw, Samuel, 1635-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 179, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by R.W. for H. Mortlock, at the White-Hart in Westminster-Hall, and at the Phœnix in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>S.S. = Samuel Shaw.</note>
                  <note>With an imprimatur statement on A2v dated May 17. 1678.</note>
                  <note>"The spiritual man in a carnal fit .. printed by M. White" (p. 117) has separate title page dated 1678; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Sion College Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXXIII, 25 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LV, 6 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:38039:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:38039:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p> THE <hi>Great Commandment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A DISCOURSE Upon <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 25.</p>
                  <p>SHEWING That God is All things to a Religious Soul.</p>
                  <p>BEING A further Explication of a ſhort Diſcourſe called, <hi>The Angelical Life,</hi> formerly Written by the ſame Author <hi>S. S.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>I <hi>laboured more abundantly than they all; yet</hi> not I, <hi>but the Grace of God which was with me,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <bibl>1 Cor. 15. 10.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <p>I <hi>live, yet</hi> not I, <hi>but Chriſt liveth in me,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <bibl>Gal. 2. 20.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart, and with all thy Soul, and with all thy Mind. This is the firſt and</hi> Great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment,</p>
                     <bibl>Mat. 22. 37; 38.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. W.</hi> for <hi>H. Mortlock,</hi> at the <hi>White-Hart</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> and at the <hi>Phoenix</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard. 1678.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="imprimatur">
                  <pb facs="tcp:38039:2"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Imprimatur Hic Liber cui titulus, The Great Commandment, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Geo. Thorp R<hi>
                           <hi rend="sup">mo.</hi>
                        </hi> in Chriſto P. &amp; D. Domino Guli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elmo Archiep. Cant. à Sacris Domeſticis.</signed>
                     <date>
                        <hi>May</hi> 17. 1678.</date>
                  </closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:38039:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:38039:3"/>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:38039:3"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To the Right Honourable and moſt Accompliſh'd Lady, the Lady</hi> Mary, <hi>Daughter to the Right Honourable the</hi> Counteſs Dowager of Huntingdon, <hi>and Conſort to M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>
                     </hi> William Jolliff <hi>of</hi> London.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>AMongſt the many Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it hath pleaſed the <hi>Father of Lights</hi> to adorn and illuſtrate you, this is not
<pb facs="tcp:38039:4"/> the leaſt of your Vertues, that you do not love to be told of them: And for my part, ſuch is the Reverend re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that I bear to your ſweet modeſty, that I fear to write what I ſuſpect your Honour would bluſh to read. In my <hi>judgement</hi> I do eſteem your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be a Perſon fit to be addreſt to for your Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of a Diſcourſe of this nature, and that I in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing am not far from the ſame circumſtances wherein the great Doctor of the Gentiles ſtood toward King <hi>Agrippa,</hi> when he accounted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf happy that he had to
<pb facs="tcp:38039:4"/> do with ſo competent a Judge. And in ingenuous <hi>gratitude</hi> I account my ſelf <hi>tantum non</hi> bound publickly to beg your peruſal and owning of this latter Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, whoſe acceptance of the former (when it was only offer'd you as a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Preſent) I found ſo kind and affectionate. I know your Honour is not aſham'd of <hi>Religion,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name nor thing, and I hope you will neither be aſham'd of, nor offended at him, who out of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere deſire to promote the happineſs of mens Souls,
<pb facs="tcp:38039:5"/> hath adventur'd to explain and recommend it to the World, though he be but,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>The meaneſt of your Honours Servants,</hi> S. S.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:38039:5"/>
                  <head>TO THE READER.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>REligion is deſervedly eſteemed the higheſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional nature, both <hi>humane</hi> and <hi>Angelical,</hi> as being the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe which the higheſt created powers and faculties maintain with the ſupreme and uncreated
<pb facs="tcp:38039:6"/> good. And it is worth obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, that even amongſt the Heathens, who yet had no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct knowledge of the true God, acquaintance with their gods, and a relation to them, was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted their greateſt glory: which made all Prophetical and Prieſtly perſons of what capacity, yea or ſex ſoever, who pretended to be Secretaries or menial ſervants to the gods, to be had in ſo great veneration. Yea the very Princes and Heroes amongſt them, though they were otherwiſe very power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, wiſe and valiant, and made no great Conſcience of being proud of it neither, were ſtill moſt ambitious which of them ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:38039:6"/> be accounted neareſt of Kin to the gods; and thoſe that pretended neareſt Kindred, gloried in that, more than in all their other accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments. Thus the great and noble and valiant <hi>Hector</hi> is brought in by <hi>Homer,</hi> as being in nothing ſhort of <hi>Minerva</hi> and <hi>Apollo,</hi> and failing of divine honour, ſave only that his extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was not immediately divine: And there you will find that the ſame <hi>Hector</hi> when he could wiſh for no greater thing, cries out,
<q>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Iliad.</hi> v.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:38039:7"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>I would I were as ſure the ſon of</hi> Jupiter, <hi>and that</hi> Juno <hi>had born me, as I will plague the</hi> Grecians <hi>this day. Virgil</hi> brings in his <hi>Aeneas</hi> glorying in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of his Piety, Counſel and Proweſs, but of nothing ſo much nor ſo often, as of his relation to <hi>Venus; Nate Deâ</hi> is the ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation that he is moſt pleaſed with. <hi>Ovid</hi> brings in the bluſtering <hi>Ajax</hi> not over modeſt indeed in telling of his Valour and Feats of Arms, but his greateſt brag of all is his<hi>—A Jove tertius Ajax</hi> And yet for the further commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Religion, it is as much, if not more obſervable, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where it put ſuch a grace upon
<pb facs="tcp:38039:7"/> all the perſons who profeſſed it, that they were had in greateſt eſtimation who were the trueſt to it, and juſtified the profeſsion of it by the ſevereſt conformity. What ever Religion hath been at any time publickly owned amongſt any Nations, ſo far as I can underſtand, hath been accounted ſo ſacred and venerable, that if any man whatſoever ſhould ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to prophane it, or in his Works to deny it, he was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the moſt profligate of all men, and not fit to live. It was ever eſteemed an honourable Character of the greateſt Princes and Heroes to be devout and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, according to the profeſſed
<pb facs="tcp:38039:8"/> Religion. If we will believe <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Agamemnon, Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> and <hi>Neſtor,</hi> and all the fam'd <hi>Grecian</hi> Heroes were pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Princes, who would ſeldom either fight, or treate, or con-conſult, or undertake any matter of moment, without the preface of a Prayer, or Sacrifice, or both. The deſpiſers of the gods and Religion, were had in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon deteſtation, and nothing could be ſaid worſe of any man, than that he was <hi>contemptor ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rûm;</hi> or as <hi>Horace</hi> calls it in his penitential Ode, <hi>Cultor Deo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum infrequens.</hi> God does by his Prophet in a wondering way make an enquiry, whether it was
<pb facs="tcp:38039:8"/> ever known that a people forſook their g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ds, who yet were no gods, <hi>Jer</hi> 2. 11. which I may well allude to, and with aſtoniſhment enquire, whether ever any people reproached and vilified their own Religion, which yet was no Religion, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted it their honor to be thought irreligious? And yet alas it is too too obvious, that in a Chriſtian Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in this Proteſtant Nation, many men do really hate that Religion which yet they do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, and account it a piece of Fanaticiſme and madneſs to be and act according to the Goſpel which they own; that is, in ſhort, to be honeſt men and true to their Words. Theſe are a generation
<pb facs="tcp:38039:9"/> of men whom one may well call prophane Hypocrites; and indeed they do not ſo much diſhonour Religion as themſelves, who like diſhoneſt men do openly oppoſe and hate what yet they openly profeſs. But there are beſides theſe another ſort of men, who knaviſhly and malignantly, but ignorantly and ſuperſtitiouſly reproach Religion. Theſe men would very honeſtly have all men to live up to their Religion: but then they make Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to be nothing elſe, but ſome Syſtematical or mechanical thing without them, by which they mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure themſelves, or unto which they make their outward man to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. And thus, whilſt they
<pb facs="tcp:38039:9"/> maintain ſuch or ſuch Opinions, or are of this or that Perſwaſion or Party, or are careful to obſerve ſuch and ſuch Modes and Forms of Worſhip, they fancy themſelves as Religious as needs to be: in the mean time being ignorant of, or little attending to that agreeable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſoul to the nature and perfections of God, which is man's Religion and only Glory. Nay ſin and Apoſtaſie is the ſinking of his ſoul from God down into ſelf and the creature; and Religion is the recovery and reſtitution of this lapſed ſoul, cauſed by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generating power of the Divine Spirit: And until the ſoul be thus raiſed, and God and his holy Will
<pb facs="tcp:38039:10"/> come to be advanc'd into a ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy in the ſoul, Religion cannot be ſaid to be, much leſs to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect there. It is to be feared that the greateſt part of men, even of thoſe men who ſpeak much of God, of His Will and Glory, of His Word and Kingdom, that ſpeak much unto Him as His <hi>Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants,</hi> and from Him as His <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours,</hi> yet ſtill fixing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Self-center, and moving with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a circle of their own, may be too truly ſaid notwithſtanding their pretenſions to Religion, to <hi>live without God in the World:</hi> and that there are infinite numbers of men, who ſcorn to be accounted <hi>Covetous,</hi> (and indeed in the
<pb facs="tcp:38039:10"/> common acceptation of the word are far from it) that yet in proper ſpeech, <hi>mind earthly things.</hi> To heal theſe diſtempers, and to rectifie theſe miſtakes, I have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured once more to explain and recommend Chriſtian Religion in this ſhort Diſcourſe; which I think, is agreeable to the holy Word of God, and which I humbly pray the ſame bleſſed God to make ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual for this end to ſome ſoul or other. I dare not ſay, I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready attain'd, but through the grace of God I can ſay, that this thing I do, <hi>viz.</hi> in my judgement renounce <hi>Self-love, Self confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Self-ſeeking,</hi> and <hi>Self-feeling,</hi> and deſire that God may
<pb facs="tcp:38039:11"/> be the object of all my <hi>Ambition, Covetouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> if I may ſo ſpeake with reverence. As I have not calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated this Diſcourſe for the palate of any one Party of men, ſo I expect the praiſe, or dread the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of none; but to the ever bleſſed God I humbly commend it for ſucceſs, and thee for edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and reſt</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Thine in Him and for His ſake,</hi> S. S.</signed>
                     <date>Nov. 26. 1677.</date>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38039:11"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>PSAL.</hi> 73. 25. Whom have I in Heaven but Thee; and there is none upon Earth that I deſire beſides Thee.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The Introduction, gueſſing at the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the</hi> Pſalm, <hi>and ſhewing the occaſion of it,</hi> viz. <hi>the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the proſperity of wicked men, and the afflicted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of good men in the World:</hi>
                        <pb n="2" facs="tcp:38039:12"/> 
                        <hi>Wherein alſo a brief account is given of the miſapprehenſions of men about that matter. A brief Explication of the Connexion of the Pſalm. The words reſolved into this Concluſion, That God is the good man's All.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT is diſputed by ſome, whether <hi>David</hi> were not the Pen man of this <hi>Pſalm,</hi> and whether he did not deliver it into the hands of <hi>Aſaph,</hi> as he is ſaid to have done ſome others, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. 7. But I think it is more generally concluded, that it was compoſed by <hi>Aſaph,</hi> for ſundry reaſons: the principal where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſeems to be that which <hi>Molle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> that learned Critick in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Language, renders, <hi>viz.</hi> for that the ſtile and Phraſe thereof doth much differ from <hi>David</hi>'s. But about this I liſt not to contend.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38039:12"/> The occaſion of it was a ſharp con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict which the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> had with himſelf, being tempted to harbour envious thoughts towards the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and hard thoughts of God and Godlineſs, by obſerving the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of evil men and the afflicted ſtate of good men in the World. This very thing hath indeed uſually been a great offence and occaſion of ſtumbling to good men in all Ages, by reaſon of that remainder of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and corrupt apprehenſions which is found even in them, they often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times judging of things more by fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and ſenſe than either by Faith, or right reaſon. It ſeemeth to me, that as the promiſes and the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the Law ſavoured more of Earth than the Goſpel doth, and were calculated for the morning of Religion rather than the Meridian of it, for the minority of men ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than their maturity; ſo that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38039:13"/> the minds even of good men under the Law, were generally more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected and influenced with worldly things than under the Goſpel. And yet it cannot be denied, but that men of the moſt refined Goſpel minds may ſometimes be ſomewhat ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized, and for the preſent ſtartled at the conſideration of the ſeeming inequality of God's dealings, which yet upon due deliberation may be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſolved, yea, and at length re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved into perfect wiſdom, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and goodneſs too. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> begins with an elegant kind of abruptneſs, laying down the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the whole in the very firſt Verſe, more like a triumphant Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour than a wrangling Diſputant. It ſeems his heart was very much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this, to aſſert and vindicate the goodneſs of God towards His people, and having been in ſome danger to have been depraved in his apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38039:13"/> concerning God, he glories in this, that he was reſolved to hold the concluſion, however he knew not well how at preſent to anſwer the premiſes. It is ſaid to the great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of <hi>Job,</hi> that <hi>he attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted nothing unſeemly to God,</hi> Job 1. although he ſeemed to deal ſo harſhly with him. And truly this doth highly concern us, to maintain right and honourable apprehenſions of God, yea though we be not able to anſwer the Arguments brought againſt him and his dealings.</p>
                     <p>Having thus briefly and patheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally aſſerted the Poſition about the controverſie aroſe, in theſe words, <hi>Truly God is good to Iſrael</hi> (which our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Meter renders very em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatically, <hi>However it be, yet God is good, and kind to Iſrael)</hi> he falls preſently upon the Narrative; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he relates a combate between faith and ſenſe, a victory that faith ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38039:14"/> and the means by which it obtained it, even by the <hi>ſword of the Spirit,</hi> which is the Word of God. At the 23 Verſe you have him come to himſelf again; and ſo the reſidue of the <hi>Pſalm</hi> is the voice of Faith alone, triumphing and glorying in God, and in the conſolation, ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and confirmation received from him.</p>
                     <p>We Tranſlate the words of the Text by way of interrogation, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying a vehement negation; others Tranſlate them in the form of a Prayer <hi>quis mihi (dabit) in coelo,</hi> &amp;c. making them the ſame in <hi>Phraſe</hi> with 2 <hi>Sam</hi> 23. 15. and the ſame in <hi>ſenſe</hi> with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. 6. But which way ſoever we Tranſlate them, the ſenſe will be much what one, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tranſlation will indifferently ſerve for the end for which I pitch upon them. For however you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs them in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the meaning
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38039:14"/> and intendment of them is to declare the dear eſteem which the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> had of God above all things in the World. Yet they are ſomewhat more emphatical to my preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, according to our Tranſlation of them, <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but Thee; and there is none upon Earth that I deſire beſides Thee.</hi> By <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> muſt needs be meant the whole Creation: If in neither of theſe the ſoul of the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt</hi> can be matcht with a ſuitable and ſatisfactory good, then certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not in the whole World: If God be better and dearer to him than both <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>Heaven,</hi> then certainly we may juſtly lay down this propoſition from the words, that</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>God is the good man's All,</hi> or that <hi>God is All things to a gracious ſoul.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:38039:15"/>
                     <head>CHAP. II. <hi>A general Deſcription of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate condition of Souls. The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Evangelical Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and true Liberty aſſerted and explained.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THE Soul of man is naturally debaſed and depraved; by falling from God it loſeth its origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and moſt natural freedom and amplitude, and ſinks into the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſettles upon a Self-center. Wicked men are ſadly pinch'd and ſtraitened by fixing their minds upon poor fading particularities; they move up and down in a narrow ſphere and circle of their own; and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38039:15"/> therefore are baſe, low and narrow-ſpirited perſons, whatever greatneſs of ſpirit and generouſneſs of mind they vainly pretend to. In this ſenſe, I'me ſure, there are none more certainly impriſon'd, nor more miſerably confin'd than they that live and converſe perpetually at home: For Self, though it be the home, yet is certainly the dungeon of the ſenſual ſoul: It is ſin alone that contracts the ſoul of man and cramps and cripples all the powers of it, ſtrangely enfeebling and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivating all its vigorous and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous faculties. But the grace of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation redeems the captive ſoul from this bondage, thaws its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gealed affections, knocks off the Chains and Fetters from its hands and feet, and ſo ſpirits all the powers thereof by its kind and powerful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuations, as that they dilate and ſpread themſelves in God, even as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38039:16"/> the poor charmed Flowers do gladly open their arms wide to entertain and welcom the beams of the Sun, and the precious influences thereof. This is indeed that <hi>Redemption</hi> which the Almighty Saviour of the World, the true diſpenſer of life and liberty, came into the World to accompliſh for us: This is the true <hi>freedom</hi> according to the Evangeliſt, <hi>John</hi> 8. 36. and he is the only pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſer and diſpenſer of it, <hi>If the Son ſhall make you free, then ſhall ye be free indeed.</hi> And this is that, which when it ſhall be perfected, ſhall be found to be <hi>the glorious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Children of God,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Apoſtles phraſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 21. Whatever other liberties and deliverances men may pretend to have by <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> certainly this is that releaſement and redemption which is ſo often ſpoken of and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by thoſe phraſes of Chriſt's
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38039:16"/> being ſent <hi>to proclaim liberty to the Captive, and the opening of the Priſon to them that are bound,</hi> (Iſa. 61. 13.) of his <hi>bringing out the Priſoners from the Priſon, and them that ſit in darkneſs out of the Priſon-houſe</hi> (Iſa. 42. 7.) of his <hi>ſaying to the Priſoners, Go forth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 9. For ſo the Apoſtle interprets this freedom, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 17. <hi>Where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is Liberty.</hi> The godly ſoul is free by <hi>Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> the true Redeemer of ſouls, and the powerful diſpenſer of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty from that ſtraitneſs and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſhneſs, under which it laboured; and endued with a noble large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and amplitude. Whereas it was formerly pinched and ſhrivel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and wrapt up in particular created goods; now it ſpends it ſelf wholly upon the uncreated goodneſs, and is as it were Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaliz'd:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38039:17"/> 
                        <hi>God is All things to the Godly Soul.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This Doctrine I ſhall explain and confirm at once in ſeveral par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:38039:17"/>
                     <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The natural underſtanding is ſunk into matter, and the imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of carnal men are groſs. Unregenerate men neglect God, and aſcribe Events to Fate or Chance, or humane Wit and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry: But the underſtandings and apprehenſions of Regenerate Souls are refin'd and ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz'd. They apprehend the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of God in all things. It is of great importance to have right and proper notions of things, eſpecially of God and of the relation in which the world ſtands to him.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>1. GOD is All things to a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man in his <hi>Aprrehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</hi> The natural underſtanding
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38039:18"/> is ſunk into matter, and pent up in poor petty particularities. The imaginations of a carnal and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate heart are groſs, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated in the outſide, or in the particular being of things: <hi>He that is of the Earth is Earthly,</hi> ſaies the <hi>Baptiſt, Joh.</hi> 3. 31. the natural wiſdom is <hi>Earthly</hi> and <hi>ſenſual,</hi> ſaies the Apoſtle, <hi>James</hi> 3. 15. Theſe fools are ready to ſay in their hearts, <hi>There is no God,</hi> Pſal. 14. 1. or if they do acknowledge a Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet they make him but a kind of an idle Spectator or Supervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, that neither does good nor evil, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1. 12. phancying to themſelves, that all things fall out in the World by a certain kind of fatality, caſualty or humane wit and induſtry. Hence you hear thoſe brags of themſelves, that they are ſome great ones, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 9. and of their Works and Atchievements,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38039:18"/> 
                        <hi>Is not this great Babel that I have built,</hi> Dan. 4. 30. <hi>I have digged and drunk waters, and with the ſole of my feet have I dryed up all the Rivers of the beſieged places,</hi> Iſa. 37. 25. They apprehend little more in the Creation, than what with their ſenſes they ſee, or hear, or taſte, or handle. One ſaies; <hi>mine own</hi> Hand hath ſaved me, <hi>Judg.</hi> 7. 21. our Lips are <hi>our own,</hi> and who is Lord over us, ſay others, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12. 4. others pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim <hi>their own</hi> goodneſs, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20. 6. will not ceaſe from <hi>their own</hi> wiſdom, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. 4. ſeek <hi>their own</hi> glory, <hi>Prov.</hi> 25. 27. <hi>My River is mine own, and I have made it for my ſelf,</hi> ſaies another, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 29. 3. <hi>We have taken to us Horns by our own ſtrength,</hi> ſay they in <hi>Amos</hi> 6. 13. <hi>By my wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, my underſtanding, my great traffique have I gotten Gold and</hi>
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:38039:19"/> 
                        <hi>Silver,</hi> cries he in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28. 4, 5. <hi>By the ſtrength of my hand, and by my wiſdom have I done it, for I am prudent: I have removed the bounds of the people, and I have put down the Inhabitants like a valiant man;</hi> thus brags the great <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Atheiſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10. 13. <hi>I have made my ſelf to differ,</hi> cries another. And ſo <hi>God is not in all their thoughts,</hi> Pſal. 10. 4. <hi>They conſider not the operation of his hands,</hi> Iſa. 5. 12. they live without the ſenſe or apprehenſion of God in the World: <hi>Ut nemo ſupra ſeſe aſcendere tentat!</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But the underſtanding and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the Godly Soul is much refined and ſpiritualized. He ſticks not in the creature, but by every thing that is <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> climbes up with the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> unto God himſelf the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and <hi>Fountain</hi> thereof. Though
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38039:19"/> the underſtandings of all good men are not made learned, yet they are all refined from ſenſual groſſneſs, and made ſomewhat Metaphyſical or ſpiritual. The godly man views not himſelf in the ſmall point of his own being, but in the infinite eſſence of God: he views not the creature in its own particular and limited exiſtence or goodneſs, but in the nature and perfections of the Creator: He looks upon the whole World as not ſubſiſting of it ſelf, nor for it ſelf, but in and for God who is above all, through all, and in all, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 6. in whom the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſtandeth, and we all live, move and have our beings, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 28. To him the whole World is as the Temple of God, all mankind, and all their ſeveral excellencies, an Image and Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traicture of God; yea, to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38039:20"/> him <hi>Monſtrat quaelibet herba De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> the Graſs of the Field reads a Divinity Lecture; In a word,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Huic Deus eſt quodcunque vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det, quodcunque movetur,</hi> He ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends the Power, Wiſdome, Perfection and Will of God in all that he ſees, does, receives or ſuſtains. Though Religion do not conſiſt in Notions, yet true, proper and ſpiritual Notions of things, eſpecially of God, and of the relation wherein the whole World, ſtands to him, are migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily conducing to it, if not a ſubſtantial part of it: So thought the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſure, when he corrected the ſuperſtitions and falſe conceits of the <hi>Athenians</hi> concerning a Deity, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. And ſo thought our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, when he would not ſuffer the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Ruler to aſcribe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38039:20"/> to him, whom he believed to be no more than a meer man, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. 19. <hi>Why calleſt thou me good? none is good ſave One, that is God.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:38039:21"/>
                     <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>God is all things to the godly man in his Affections. The Deſires of Unregenerate men run out only after Creature good. The Objection of wicked men having good deſires, anſwered: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is ſhewed that all deſires of good are not good deſires, and an account given of it. Men may be carnal in their deſiring of ſpiritual good.</hi> James 4. 3. <hi>explained, wherein is ſhewed how many waies men ſeek their own luſts inſtead of God, and the carnality which may be found in Prayers that ſeem ſpiritual. God is All to the godly man in his deſires of things</hi>
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:38039:21"/> 
                        <hi>temporal, and in his hopes of Heaven.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>2. GOD is <hi>All</hi> things to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man in his Affections. The wicked man as he views him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in himſelf, and the ſeveral crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in themſelves, ſo he loves and delights in himſelf and the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as ſomething diſtinct from God. But the godly ſoul endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours by all means to keep all his affections pure and chaſt for God alone. Now in as much as the affections of the ſoul are many, it will be neceſſary to explain the matter in ſome particulars.</p>
                     <p>1. God is <hi>All</hi> to the godly man in his <hi>deſires</hi> and <hi>cravings,</hi> in his lookings and waitings, in his hopes and expectations. I put all theſe together under one Head, becauſe they ſeem to be much what the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38039:22"/> ſame, or at leaſt of great affinity one to another. The deſires and appetites of the unregenerate ſoul do run out only after creature good, ſelf accommodations and things that do gratifie the meer animal life. Thus the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> deſcribes their temper, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. 6. <hi>Many ſay, Who will ſhew us any good:</hi> which our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Meter interprets very truly, <hi>The greater ſort crave worldly goods.</hi> That is a ſhort, but yet a very true and full deſcription that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> makes of theſe men, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 19. <hi>They mind Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things.</hi> It were eaſie to be large here in demonſtrating (in a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral way) that there is nothing in the worldly nature, but the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eye, and the pride of life; according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution which the Apoſtle makes, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 16. But I ſhall not fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſiſt upon that general. It
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:38039:22"/> ſeems as if wicked men ſometimes had good deſires and good wiſhes; and indeed it cannot be denied but that ſome of their deſires are <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terially</hi> good: who can ſay but that of <hi>Balaam</hi> was a good wiſh, as to the matter of it, <hi>Numb.</hi> 23. 10. <hi>Let me die the death of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and let my laſt end be like his;</hi> It was materially a <hi>good wiſh</hi> (though a <hi>bad bargain)</hi> of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus,</hi> that by the impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his hands men might receive the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 19. It is not to be doubted but that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wicked men, yea perhaps the moſt of them, at one time or other, do heartily deſire that their ſins may be pardoned, and their ſouls ſaved, and they go to Heaven; according to that of our Saviour, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. 28. <hi>Many will ſeek to enter in and ſhall not be able.</hi> But however theſe may ſeem to be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38039:23"/> good deſires, yet they are not real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo: All <hi>deſires of good</hi> are not <hi>good deſires:</hi> If men ſhould deſire the preſence of Chriſt in glory, and the Kingdom of Heaven, in ſubordination to ſelf, and ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viency to a fleſhly intereſt, it would be ſo far from being indeed a good, that it would ſcarce be a lawful, it may be a blaſphemous wiſh. And it is very clear, that all the ſeeming good wiſhes, and prayers, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of unſanctified minds are ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timately reſolved into a fleſhly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and ſelf gratification. It is not God, but themſelves that they really ſeek, even then when they deſire him to be at peace with them, and that they might be with him in his Kingdom. It is only true of all unregenerate men which the Apoſtle affirms of all men, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 21. <hi>All men ſeek their own things, and not the things</hi>
                        <pb n="25" facs="tcp:38039:23"/> 
                        <hi>which are Jeſus Chriſts;</hi> and this holds good of them, not only when they are with <hi>Saul</hi> ſeeking their Aſſes, or with <hi>Abſolom</hi> ſeeking an earthly Kingdom; but even then when they are ſeeking to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdom of God.</p>
                     <p>But God is <hi>All</hi> in the deſires and prayers and hopes of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoul. The whole World is too ſhort a bed for ſuch a ſoul to ſtretch it ſelf upon. The appetites and cravings of ſuch a ſoul being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited and awakened by the ſenſe of its own large and excellent ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, the inadequateneſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency of the creature, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite ſelf-ſufficiency and ſweetneſs, and ſuitableneſs of God the ſupreme good, cannot poſſibly fix or reſt or terminate themſelves in any thing below him, and the enjoyment of him. Thus the deſires of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are deſcribed by the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:38039:24"/> oppoſition to the luſtings of the wicked, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. 6. <hi>Lord, lift thou up the light of thy countenance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us:</hi> And ſo in the words of the Text, if they be underſtood by way of prayer, <hi>Who will give me to be in Heaven with thee?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The prayers of the wicked al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they may be for things good and lawful, yet are ultimately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved into ſelf-gratification: They may be as fluent in words, as loud in their cries, as hearty and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent in their requeſts as other men: If it be for Corn, and Wine, and Oyl, they can roar and howl as loud as the beſt, and yet this is not interpreted as ſeeking of God, but of themſelves, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7. 17. <hi>They have not cryed unto me with their heart, when they howled upon their beds; They aſſemble themſelves for Corn and for Wine,</hi> &amp;c. That is a very memorable expreſſion of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:38039:24"/> Apoſtle <hi>James, Jam.</hi> 4. 3. <hi>Ye ask amiſs, that ye may conſume it upon your luſts.</hi> Which indeed is the deſign of unregenerate ſouls, even when they ſeem to pray for things in their own nature ſpiritual. Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men are <hi>carnal</hi> even in praying for <hi>ſpiritual</hi> things. But godly men are not ſo; they are ſo far from that, that on the contrary, they are ſpiritual in praying for carnal and earthly things. They wrap up a Prayer in a Prayer; they have a farther reach than the meer enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the creature, when they pray for creature good; a higher end than the pleaſing and ſerving of themſelves, when they pray for themſelves, or their own private and perſonal concernments. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it is not only an abſurd, but a monſtrous and blaſphemous thing for any man to pray to God to fulfil his luſts; the intereſt of God
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:38039:25"/> being ſo perfectly contrary to the intereſt of carnal ſelf. And yet I fear there are very many that do thus interpretatively blaſpheme God, even in their Prayers, when they pretend to honour him; and theſe ſometimes, perhaps, not of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry worſt of men neither. What would it have been elſe but a pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of luſt, if the two Diſciples had been ſuffered to have prayed for fire from Heaven upon the heads of the poor <hi>Samaritans,</hi> to revenge their Maſter's quarrel, as they would have done, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9. 24? What was it elſe but a prayer of luſt when the ſame two Diſciples petitioned their Lord for the chiefeſt place and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence in his Kingdom, <hi>Mark</hi> 10. 37? Only our gracious Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our was pleaſed ſomewhat to excuſe them, by reaſon of their ignorance, <hi>Ye know not what manner of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ye are of;</hi> and again, <hi>Ye know</hi>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:38039:25"/> 
                        <hi>not what ye ask.</hi> I will not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute how far a devout and well meaning ſoul may pray upon a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, nor how far ſuch a ſoul may poſſibly miſtake the intereſt of his luſts, for the intereſt of Religion, and the Kingdom of Chriſt: But methinks ſuch miſtakes are very dangerous, and much more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and inexcuſable now, than they were in the daies of the Son of Man. And yet as dangerous as they are, I fear they are too too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon even in theſe daies. Charity covereth a multitude of ſins indeed, but yet it is the endowment of a rational ſoul; and ſo the Charity that is ſtark blind, is no Charity: Yea, I may add, that it is the part of Charity to <hi>diſcover</hi> a multitude of ſins before the eyes of thoſe that commit them, as well as to <hi>cover</hi> them before ones own. It is too evident (if we compare the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:38039:26"/> talk and temper of men with their devotions, and if with their prayers you compare their practices which they uſe in purſuit of them,) that paſſion, revenge and ſelf-inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt do indite the prayers of many that ſeem to be zealous for the Lord; every thing is Anti-chriſtian, that is contrary to their opinion, eaſe or intereſt; and then is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt exalted, when they themſelves are advanced into a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, honourable and ruling ſtate. What if it ſhould come to paſs that ſome, even of them that ſeem to be moſt forward to ſit at the right and left hand of Chriſt in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſhould be found to ſtand on his left hand with the impure Goats, in the day of the deciſion of all things? And what can we ſay of thoſe animoſe and furious ſtrivings and groanings of men in prayer, againſt all that diſſent from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:38039:26"/> but that their prayers are rather the bublings and boylings up of intereſt, than the language of the pure, peaceable and gentle ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God. I fear theſe mens prayers are not put up <hi>without wrath,</hi> as the Apoſtle exhorts, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 8. and I wiſh their hands be found ſo holy as they ſhould be, if ever they have opportunity to uſe them. Nay, what if many of our moſt fervent and affectionate groanings after deliverance, liberty and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption from afflictions and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions (as innocent as they ſeem to be) ſhould be found to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but the raging of our own animal paſſions, and ſuch pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers as an oppreſſed Beaſt might put up as well as we, if he could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs them ſo affectionately. I know it is very lawful and warrantable to put up prayers unto God for relief in our troubles, and releaſe from our
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38039:27"/> preſſures; but yet it is no more than what is natural unto men, no more than what <hi>Jonah</hi>'s heatheniſh Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners did as well as he. Man ſeeks for deliverance from troubles pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly as an <hi>animal,</hi> not as a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</hi> And if this be All we aim at in our prayers, they will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted (if not as a begging for our luſts, yet) as meer breathings of the Animal life, and out-cries of our own ſenſual affections, no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fruit than may be found upon Publicans; <hi>For do not even the Publicans the ſame?</hi> But this is not all that the Godly ſoul aims at in his prayers and hopes; but God is <hi>All</hi> in his hopes whether of things in this World, or in another.</p>
                     <p>It is not the meer naked abſtract enjoyment of proſperity, liberty, or life it ſelf in this World, that the godly ſoul ſo vehemently looks, longs, prays and hopes for; but it
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:38039:27"/> is ſome real communication <hi>from</hi> God, or ſomething that may capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate him <hi>for</hi> God in all theſe. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that is wronged and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, would gladly be righted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered; But the godly man ſets not his heart ſo much upon his own eaſe; as upon the honour of God, and the intereſt of Truth and righteouſneſs, which he deſires may take place in the World. Every man would be great; but the good man alone ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of worldly power meerly for this end, that by his authority he may the better ſerve the honour of his great God; which ſeems to have been purely <hi>David</hi>'s deſign, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75. 2. <hi>When I ſhall receive the Congregation, I will judge upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> Victory is ſweet and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all; but that truth ſhould be mighty and prevail, that equity and juſtice ſhould triumph in the World, this is dear and deſirable only to the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:38039:28"/> godly ſoul, the ſoul that is purified from earthly and ſelfiſh loves. The meer worldly life deſires worldly li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; but that higher principle which is ſeated in the godly ſoul, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vets a more ſpiritual and excellent freedom, even the glorious liberty of the Sons of God. Life is ſweet to all; but to the godly Soul to be without God, would not be to live, <hi>For his loving kindneſs is better than life,</hi> Pſal. 63. 3. In a word, it is the intereſt of God and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him, which ſpirits and impregnates all the hopes and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations of the renewed ſoul, which he conceives concerning earthly things.</p>
                     <p>And if this be ſo, it need not be doubted but that God is <hi>All</hi> to him in his hopes concerning the World to come, the <hi>All</hi> of Heaven. I fear there are many Chriſtians that are high in their own hopes of Heaven
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:38039:28"/> and of their going thither, who lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle think of God there, and are lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle acquainted with the ſpiritual na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of right happineſs. But God is All of Heaven it ſelf to a right gracious ſoul: The great thing which he hopes for in the world to come, is to be perfected in the image of God, and live everlaſtingly in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him. And therefore when the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of his departure out of this world, he gives us to underſtand what was moſtly in his eye and upon his heart, and that was to be with Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 23. And the Apoſtle <hi>John,</hi> when he ſpeaks of the glory and bleſſedneſs of a future ſtate, deſcribes it by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance that the ſoul ſhall bear to God at that time, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 2. <hi>When he ſhall appear, we ſhall be like unto him.</hi> Heaven is but a name and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without God, God himſelf is not the happineſs of a ſoul except he
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:38039:29"/> be enjoyed, and he can no other way be enjoyed but by a ſpiritual union with him, and aſſimilation to him. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> in the Text ſignifies either who or what: Now then there are many that are for eaſe, many for peace and liberty, many for pomp and preeminence in Heaven; But our <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> hath nothing deſireable, no not there, but God alone; <hi>Whom have I,</hi> or <hi>what have I in Heaven but thee?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:38039:29"/>
                     <head>CHAP. V. <hi>God is All to the godly man in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and pleaſure. The plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of wicked men are ſenſual. There are degrees of ſenſuality amongſt carnal men. The delight that an unregenerate man takes in ſpiritual things is carnal. The godly ſoul feeds upon God in every thing: He loves and admires his own ſoul in God. Grace does not overthrow the judgement of ſenſe, but it regulates the ſenſes as to their actings, and enables the ſoul to delight in things ſenſual, in a ſuper ſenſual manner.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>2. GOD is All to the godly man in his <hi>Delight</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure.</hi> As the appetites of the unregenerate ſoul are ſenſual, ſo are his ſentiments
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38039:30"/> and reſentments. This muſt needs follow; as indeed it doth follow in the fourth <hi>Pſalm:</hi> their <hi>deſire</hi> is, <hi>Who will ſhew us any good,</hi> verſ. 6. their <hi>delight</hi> is in <hi>Corn and Wine,</hi> and in the encreaſe of them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. They know no higher good than peace, plenty, liberty and length of daies; know not how to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain themſelves any better than by ſitting down to eat and drink, and riſing up to play. Thus you find the deſport and jovialty of the wicked deſcribed, <hi>Job</hi> 21. 10, 11, 12, 13. <hi>Am.</hi> 6. 4, 5, 6. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 19. and many other places. But you will ſay, theſe are a groſſer ſort of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualiſts; all wicked men ſure are not ſo brutiſh, ſo ſwiniſh as to wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in ſuch kind of mire as this is. I confeſs they do not all welter in the ſame mire; there are almoſt as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny kind of Idolaters, as there are kinds of creatures to be idolized.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:38039:30"/> There ſeems to be a greater and leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer brutiſhneſs amongſt the brutes themſelves; a Sheep will not wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in the mire like a Swine, nor a Pidgeon feed upon ſuch ſtinking Carrion as a Crow, and yet they are brutes as well as they. All wicked ſouls do not feed upon the ſame husks, but all feed upon husks that have forſaken the bread of their Father's houſe. There are ſeveral ſorts of Diſhes whereupon the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life feeds. Luſt is oft-times fed by things materially good, as well as by thoſe that are materily evil. A man may be as unchaſt and adulterous with his own gifts and parts, as with his neighbours Wife, and a woman may fall into as unclean dalliances with her own beauty, as with a man that is not her Husband. The Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical life (when men adore their own ſouls, and feed upon their own perfections) is as truly unholy and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:38039:31"/> unclean, though not altogether ſo groſs, as that which is meer ſenſual. And thus I doubt not but that many of the Stoical Philoſophers, with their <hi>Autaeſtheſie</hi> and ſelf-enjoyment, were as unclean and idolatrous, as the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curean Atheiſts with all their meats and drinks and ſtrange fleſh.</p>
                     <p>Yea though the unregenerate mind ſhould be much delighted with the outward dreſs and diſpenſation of Religion, as they were in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. 31, 32. yea though it ſhould be mightily pleaſed and tickled with the notions of God's Free-grace, Juſtification by the blood of Jeſus, an everlaſting inheritance in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe of God, and ſuch ſpiritual things as theſe (as I do eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it may) yet were his delight, that he takes in theſe very things, unclean and earthly: For ſtill it is reſolved into this, it is ſelf and not God which he ultimately takes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in.</p>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:38039:31"/>
                     <p> But God is <hi>All</hi> in the delights and complacencies of the truly godly ſoul. He delights not in himſelf or any other creature abſtractly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and in ſeparation from God. It is ſaid of one (I think it is of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin)</hi> that after his converſion he could take no pleaſure in <hi>Cicero</hi>'s Orations, becauſe he could not find the name of <hi>Chriſt</hi> there: but ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a good ſenſe the name of <hi>Chriſt</hi> may be ſaid to be inſcribed, and ſomething of his image drawn upon every creature; for by him all things were made, and he hath copyed out ſomething of his own perfections up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them all: And this is that which the holy and wiſe ſoul gathers up and feeds upon with delight. I know indeed that Grace doth not deſtroy natural affections in men, no nor overthrow the judgement of ſenſe; but it doth certainly confer upon men a far more excellent and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:38039:32"/> faculty of diſcerning and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting. What I ſaid before con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſpirituality of a godly man's deſires of Heaven and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, may be applied to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights alſo. But I conceive that the greateſt doubt doth not lie there. Therefore as to the pleaſurable ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of this World; whereof the chiefeſt ſeems to be a man's own ſoul, The godly man loves, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires and reverences his own ſoul no leſs, but much more purely, than any other man. He admires the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite and uncreated wiſdom, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, love, life, liberty, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playing and diſcovering it ſelf in the conſtitution of his own mind, Free-will, and Affections, and the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent capacities and functions of theſe faculties: and ſo by giving God the glory of his wonderful making <hi>(Pſal.</hi> 139. 14.) he eſcapes the brand of a <hi>ſelf-admirer.</hi> There
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:38039:32"/> are many other objects of delight in this World, all which it is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per work of Divine Grace to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualize to the ſoul; ſuch as food and raiment, Houſes and Lands, Friends and Relations, and many the like. It cannot be denied, but that the godly man loves his friends, his Wife and Children and Parents with a natural love; but he loves them alſo, and all that is lovely in them, with a ſpiritual love, which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant: that by which they are any of them pleaſant and amiable, he underſtands to be a communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God unto them, and under that notion labours to reliſh them moſt of all. Whilſt we are in this bodily mixt ſtate, we cannot be freed from a delight that is meerly ſenſual. Meat and drink (no doubt) affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted our Saviours ſenſe, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded the ſame reliſh to his palate, whilſt he had an animal body, as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:38039:33"/> they afforded to other mens, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he was ſo infinitely pure and ſpiritual, as that it was his meat and drink to be doing the Will of God. The power of Grace doth not ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble any man not to taſte a ſweetneſs or bitterneſs in things that are really ſweet or bitter: It does not fall under the power of my reaſon or will, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no I will reliſh or ſenſate the ſweetneſs of my morſel; I cannot help that, although I can keep my ſelf from eating it: ſo then it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fall under the power of grace. But although Grace do not deſtroy the ſenſation of the ſenſes, yet it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulates and moderates all the ſenſes, as to their actings. Hence <hi>Job</hi> is ſaid to have made a Covenant with his eyes, <hi>Job</hi> 31. 1. and <hi>David</hi> to have kept his mouth as with a bridle, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39. 1. And as it governs the ſenſes as to their actings, ſo it alſo beſtowes a more excellent ability up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:38039:33"/> the ſoul to delight it ſelf in things ſenſual, in a ſuperſenſual way and manner. Beſides the pleaſure of the ſenſes, which is animal and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all men, yea indeed and beaſts alſo, the gracious ſoul doth reliſh ſomething Divine, ſomething of God, his Love, his communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in all delectable objects, which confers upon them a tranſcendent ſubſtantial ſweetneſs. And thus he may be ſaid to taſte God in every morſel, to ſmell the Divinity in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Flower, and to converſe with him by a kind of ſecret feeling in all that he touches, taſtes or handles in the World.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:38039:34"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>God is All to the godly man in his Truſt and Confidence. The crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-confidence of carnal men is Blaſphemy. Good men are afraid of diſtruſt: How great reckoning they have alwaies made of their Faith. The only fear of carnal men is the violation of ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. God is All in the fears of good men. They fear him only, though they are not afraid of him. God is All to the godly man in his grief and ſorrow explained.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>3. GOD is All to the godly man in his Truſt and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. The degenerate and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate ſoul as it is ſunk into the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:38039:34"/> creature, ſo it ſticks there; it ſticks by love and delight, and ſticks faſt by confidence. It were endleſs to give you but the Scripture inſtances of Self-confidence and Creature-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance. In Creature-confidence there is much Atheiſm, or rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed blaſphemy: For to aſcribe that firmneſs, faithfulneſs, ſufficiency, which God alone is, to any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides him, muſt needs be blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and idolatrous. And thus do wicked men blaſpheme, whilſt they lay the ſtreſs of their ſouls upon the Arm of fleſh, upon Chariots and Horſe men, upon friends and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, upon carnal intereſts or world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly riches: And thus we know they do, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 20. 7. <hi>Some truſt in Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots, and ſome in Horſes.</hi> Prov. 18. 11. <hi>The rich man's wealth is his ſtrong City, and as a high Wall in his own conceit.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:38039:35"/>
                     <p> But godly men have God alone for their refuge and confidence, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of the wiſe King, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18. 10. <hi>The Name of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower, the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous run into it and are ſafe.</hi> I know they may be, and often are ſurprized with fears and doubts, but yet even then they will not let go their hold of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56. 3. <hi>What time I am afraid I will truſt in thee.</hi> It is as much the part of a godly ſoul to relye and reſt upon God, as to love him and pray unto him; he is afraid of diſtruſt, unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, and caſting away his confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as well as of Drunkenneſs or Debauchery. I cannot but take notice what great reckoning the Saints have made of their Faith, as if the very life of their ſouls had been bound up in it. How expreſly and pathetically does the Apoſtle charge us concerning this, <hi>Epheſ.</hi>
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:38039:35"/> 6. 16. <hi>Above all taking the Shield of Faith;</hi> and again, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 23. <hi>Let us hold faſt the profeſſion of our Faith, without wavering;</hi> and again, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 35. <hi>Caſt not away your confidence which hath great recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of reward. Job</hi> when he had loſt all, yet reſolves not to part with his Faith, whatever became of him, <hi>Job</hi> 13. 15. <hi>Though he ſlay me yet I will truſt in him.</hi> And doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs an ingenuous and ſteady reliance upon the grace and ſtrength and help of God alone, is an excellent argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a ſound and gracious ſoul. Good men know how to make uſe of ſecond cauſes, and they ſee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly as far into all creature-proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, as any other men; but it is the vertue and ſtrength of God that they reſt upon in all means and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments.</p>
                     <p>4. God is <hi>All</hi> to the godly ſoul in his fears. The ungodly are full of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:38039:36"/> worldly fears, ſlaviſh fears, ſcarce ever free from fears about one thing or other; yea though there be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing viſible to make them afraid: But as their intereſt is bound up in ſelf and this preſent World, ſo their great and only fear is concerning the violation of this ſelf-intereſt. He that hath plac'd his happineſs in the enjoyment of any created good, hath made a miſerable choice, for he is in danger of being utterly ruin'd every hour; all created good being ſubject to ſo many ſpoilers, that a man can never be ſecure in his poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion. And therefore no wonder that his heart is haunted one while with the fears of death, another while with the fears of loſſes, loſs of Friends or Children, loſs of Goods or Reputation, fears of wants, fears of diſgrace, and many things more which his ſlaviſh heart is aw'd with continually.</p>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:38039:36"/>
                     <p> But God is <hi>All</hi> in the fears of good men; <hi>He is their fear and their dread.</hi> as the phraſe is, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8. 13. Not that they are properly afraid of God (for they diſcover nothing in him but what is moſt amiable and grateful to them, and therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with him as with love it ſelf, ſerve him as accounting it their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and intereſt to do ſo, and obey his Commands as thoſe which are moſt equitable, and ſuitable, and moſt perfective of their natures, with all gladneſs and chearfulneſs) but they are afraid of ſin, ſo as wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men are afraid of ſickneſs and death, <hi>viz.</hi> as that which is hurtful to them and deſtructive of their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. Sin is all their fear, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the oppoſition it bears to the pure nature of God; and ſo it may be ſaid that God is <hi>All</hi> in their fear. Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeems to have been more ſolicitous for the <hi>honour of God,</hi> than
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:38039:37"/> for the <hi>preſervation of the whole Congregation;</hi> and more afraid of the <hi>ſin</hi> of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> than of the <hi>death</hi> of the <hi>Iſraelites, Numb.</hi> 14. 13, 14, 15, 16. whereunto many more Inſtances might be added.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, To name no more of the Affections, God is <hi>All things</hi> to the godly ſoul in his <hi>grief.</hi> Concerning the ſorrow of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one, I may ſay partly the ſame as I ſaid even now concerning their fears; it is a worldly ſorrow, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from, and terminated in the Creature. But the ſorrow of the godly ſoul is a godly ſorrow. He is grieved indeed for many things; but ſtill the reaſon of his grief is derived ſome way or other from God. He grieves when he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured or Perſecuted; but there is a hidden cauſe of his grief; he is not ſo much troubled that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:38039:37"/> is injured, or his own perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal intereſt wounded, as that truth and righteouſneſs are violated there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and God diſhonoured. He grieves over the Wars and Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, confuſions and diſtractions that are in the Kingdom, <hi>as well as</hi> other men; but yet not <hi>as</hi> other men; for he moſt of all laies to heart the luſts of men, which as the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks, are the occaſion and Original of them. He grieves over his Loſſes, of Goods, Children, Liberty and the like; and yet not ſo much over his Loſſes, to ſpeak properly, as over the cauſe and conſequent of them, as he apprehends ſin to be the cauſe of them, or that himſelf ſhall be ſome way or other ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred leſs ſerviceable to God by them. I ſuppoſe no man in this World is ſo far refined, perfected and exalted in his nature, as to be
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:38039:38"/> altogether free from the affections and paſſions that are meerly natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and animal: A good man's tears are of the ſame kind of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as other mens are of, though poſſibly not altogether from the ſame Fountain; or if from the ſame Fountain, yet they are pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified from much of that mud and acrimony that cleave to other mens. When the Women that attended upon <hi>Phineas</hi> his Wife in her tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail endeavoured to comfort her fainting ſpirit with the tidings of a Son, ſhe made no anſwer at all to that, but ſhe does as good in effect as tell them, That they miſtook her grief, when ſhe called the Child <hi>Icabod,</hi> ſignifying thus much, that the departure of <hi>Irael</hi>'s glory did more affect and oppreſs her heart, than all her other pangs, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. I do not read that ever all <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s enemies wrung ſuch plenty of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:38039:38"/> tears from his eyes, as the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of God did, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 136. nor that all <hi>Paul</hi>'s Perſecutions ever wrung ſuch a groan from him, as the ſenſe of his own ſin did, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 24. <hi>O wretched man that I am,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:38039:39"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>The unſanctified man performs all his natural, civil and ſacred Actions in, to, and for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, though there may be ſome difference in the external groſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. To a godly man, God is the ſpring and end of all his actions. The notion of deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all things for God and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting them to his glory ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, and how a man may be Religious in the very natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and civil actions of his life. The Sacrilegious ſelfiſhneſs of carnal men in their ſacred acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
                        <pb n="57" facs="tcp:38039:39"/> 
                        <hi>diſcovered. The contrary temper of the regenerate ſoul.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WE have ſeen that God is All to the godly ſoul as to his <hi>Apprehenſions</hi> and <hi>Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>3. God is <hi>All things</hi> to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoul in his <hi>Actions.</hi> Actions are either <hi>Natural, Civil</hi> or <hi>Sacred:</hi> All which the wicked man perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>in,</hi> and <hi>to,</hi> and <hi>for</hi> himſelf: He eats and drinks, and embraces, and performs all other animal acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as any other Creature doth, for the gratification of his meer ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal appetite, and the ſatisfaction of his own ſenſual luſt. What can be more plain? <hi>Whoſe God is their Belly,</hi> ſaies the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 19. whoſe ultimate end is the ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their ſenſes. By <hi>God</hi> muſt needs be underſtood their ultimate
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:38039:40"/> end, and by their <hi>Belly</hi> muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the pleaſing and fulfilling their ſenſual appetites. So it is in his Civil actions: He Ploughs and Sows, Fights and Studies, Plants and Builds, confers and conſults, and all to and for himſelf. It were eaſie to demonſtrate and explain each of theſe in particular: but in any one we prove all. <hi>The ploughing of the wicked, is ſin,</hi> ſaies <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 21. 4. which certainly it would not be if it were deſigned and performed for God, as it ought to be; but it is deſigned ultimately for ſelf, and that makes it ſinful. I know, all wicked men are not ſo groſs as to brag of their Buildings openly with the <hi>Chaldean</hi> Monarch, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. <hi>This is Babylon that I have built by the might of my power, and for the honour of my Majeſty:</hi> All that go out to fight, do not in words boaſt and magnifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:38039:40"/> againſt God, as the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Monarch did, of which you read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10. but the ſecret Genius and temper of them all is alike, they have all one heart. It is as proper to ſay the luſt of Ploughing, Plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Studying, Fighting, as of Eating and Drinking. Yea, and thus it is in his ſacred actions too; he ſerves himſelf when he pretends more eſpecially to ſerve God in the Acts of Worſhip. I do not think that all are ſo groſs as <hi>Jezabel</hi> in proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and celebrating Faſts: but it is moſt clear that the moſt ſolemn Acts, and the moſt ſanctimonious ſervices of wicked men are a meer piece of ſuperſtition, terminated in ſelf-accommodation, and reſolved into a fleſhly intereſt. Hence it is that you have God flatly denying, and diſowning their very prayers, and ſaying expreſly they were not prayers to him, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7. 4. you have
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:38039:41"/> him plainly forbidding ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upbraiding them and cloathing them with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachful names, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. 3. yea ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horring and abominating their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, incenſe and ſacrifices, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28. 9. 21. 27. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 13. And no wonder that ſuch Sacrifices ſhould be an abomination unto God; for to ſpeak properly, the things which theſe ſuperſtitious minds do ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, they ſacrifice to ſelf, and the intereſt of fleſh, and not to God.</p>
                     <p>But God is <hi>All</hi> to the godly man in all theſe ſorts of actions. God is the ſpring of them, and the end of them all. He undertakes all in the name and ſtrength of God, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. It is not he that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieveth ought, but God by him. <hi>I laboured,</hi> ſaies the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, more abundantly than they all,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 10. but preſently he cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects himſelf, as if he had ſpoken
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:38039:41"/> raſhly, <hi>Yet not I, but the grace of God that was with me. David</hi> makes his boaſt in God at all times, and in all things happily performed: <hi>By my God have I leap'd over a Wall;</hi> and again, <hi>By my God have I ran through a Troop,</hi> Pſal. 18. 29.</p>
                     <p>And he deſigns all his actions <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely,</hi> and as much as may be <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly</hi> for God. When I ſay, that he deſigns all his actions for God, I do not mean, that he frames a diſtinct notion of God in his mind, when ever he undertakes any thing; but he doth all things for good, and for the advancement of truth, peace, righteouſneſs, and holineſs in the World. He eyes that which is good, juſt, ſober, temperate, chaſt, pure and decorous in all the natural and civil actions of his life, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the appetite and intereſt of the fleſh. If I Plough or Sow,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:38039:42"/> Eat or Drink, Build or Plant, Fight or Study, or conſult with reference to the command of God, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the advancement of the Kingdom of Chriſt in my own ſoul, or in the World, or to ſome end higher than the pleaſing of my fleſh, and the gratification of my animal paſſions; I may be ſaid to do that for God, although I do not directly meditate upon the Being of God at that time. And ſo the Religious Chriſtian even in his recreations (which of all civil actions may ſeem to be moſt alien from a Religious deſign) may truly eye and ſerve God. If we were ſo abſtracted from ſenſe, and purified from fleſh-pleaſing, as were to be deſired, we might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the health of our bodies, and the exoneration of our minds by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations, and ſerve God as truly by them, as by taking either food or Phyſick: yea though we did receive
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:38039:42"/> a ſatisfaction from thoſe things which are purely ſenſual (a thing which we cannot hinder) yet might we be ſaid to be ſuperſenſual and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious in thoſe very acts: For it is not the having of animal ſenſes, no nor the pleaſing of them as ſuch, that is our fault; but our ſacrificing to, and being ſunk into the animal life, this is our ſin and ſhame, and miſery. He that doth work or play, Marry or give in marriage, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely reſpecting the true good of his ſoul, cannot be ſaid to be ſenſual in ſuch actions, although his ſenſes may, and indeed will have their part in the delights thereof. All things cannot be ſaid to be done for fleſh-pleaſing, in which it falls out that the fleſh is pleaſed. For ſome of thoſe very actions that are princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally deſigned and calculated for the glory of God and the intereſt of the ſoul, may yet indifferently ſerve for
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:38039:43"/> the gratification of the ſenſes, and the entertainment of this animal bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; as may eating and drinking, though it be directly to the <hi>glory of God;</hi> and Marrying, though it be never ſo much <hi>in the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In his ſacred Actions, there the godly ſoul is yet more ſpiritual and refined: Here is indeed no great danger of ſenſuality, properly ſo called; and yet here the wicked man can make a ſhift to be carnally-minded and ſelfiſh, as you have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready heard. But in theſe kind of actions God is <hi>All</hi> to the godly ſoul: He feels not himſelf in theſe, he ſeeks not himſelf by them. O how common a thing is it for men to carry an image of themſelves before their eyes, even in the things that they pretend to do for God! I ſuppoſe <hi>Jehu</hi> was no little fond of himſelf, and his own valourouſneſs, and thought God was not a little endebt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:38039:43"/> to him for it, when he calls for witneſſes and ſpectatours of it, <hi>Come ſee my zeal for the Lord.</hi> And truly the Sacrilegious ſelfiſhneſs of other men is as great, though not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſo groſs, who although they do not ſo loudly proclaim them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, nor ſet up ſuch viſible Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phees of their own prayers, yet do magnifie themſelves in their own eyes, and ſecretly applaud them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in an unhallowed ſenſe of their own Atchievements and attainments. But the truly Religion ſoul though he cannot but know his own worth and excellencies, yet knows it not, no delights not in it as his own, but as a communication of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty goodneſs, and infinite perfection of God unto him. When he ſhines moſt gloriouſly in the exerciſes of gifts and the actings of grace, he does not preſently fall in love with his own picture, dote upon his own
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:38039:44"/> perfections, nor wantonly dally with his own gifts; but looks upon his luſtre only as a poor reflection of the divine light and glory, which hath ſpread it ſelf upon him. As a rendring nothing to God but what is indeed his own; <hi>Of thine own have we given thee, and all this ſtore cometh of thine hand, and is all thine own,</hi> 1 Chron. 29. 14, 16. Have ye not read how ſharply the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> takes up the wondring Jews, that ſeemed not to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge God in the miraculous cure wrought upon the Crepple, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 12. <hi>Ye men of Iſrael, why look ye ſo earneſtly on us, as if by our own power and holineſs we had made this man to walk!</hi> The god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man feels not himſelf in his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious performances: neither does he ſeek himſelf by them. He makes not Religion a piece of p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>licy, nor ſerves himſelf of God when he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:38039:44"/> to ſerve him; as that hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical Generation did, of whom our Saviour ſpeaks, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. 14. who made long prayers in ſubſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency to oppreſſion; and after him his Apoſtle <hi>James, Jam.</hi> 4. 3. who prayed on purpoſe that they might have to ſpend upon their luſts. This hath been a very reigning ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the world. Did <hi>Saul,</hi> think ye, properly ſeek God, or himſelf and his own ſafety in thoſe <hi>forced</hi> burnt-offerings of his which he ſpeaks of in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. 12. <hi>Therefore I ſaid, the Philiſtines will come down now upon me to Gilgal, and I have not made ſupplication unto the Lord; I forced my ſelf therefore and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered a burnt-offering?</hi> Did <hi>Judas,</hi> think ye, properly ſeek the honour of God, or himſelf and his own en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riching, when he made a motion for giving three hundred pence to the poor? Let the Spirit of God be
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:38039:45"/> Judge of this, whoſe determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you will find in <hi>Joh.</hi> 12. 6. Some ſerve their own covetouſneſs, ſome ſeek their own ſafety, ſome ſtudy to advance their own name and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by their Faſtings, Prayers and Alms: But a godly ſoul is a ſtranger to all theſe low and ſorry ends: It is not wealth, nor fame, nor peace, nor victory over his enemies, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from diſtreſſes, no nor any other external glory, or <hi>only</hi> reward in another World, which he purſues in his Religious courſe: But he draws nigh to God, that God may draw nigh to him; he waits upon him in Duties and Ordinances, waiting for communications from him; he knows nothing better than God himſelf, for which he ſhould ſerve him; he accounts his end, happineſs and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to reſemble him and grow up in him. In a word, he does not only perform the duties of Religion, as
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:38039:45"/> being <hi>God's Work,</hi> which he hath ſet him about, and promiſed a reward unto; but indeed as <hi>his own work,</hi> his own buſineſs; he reckons it the true intereſt of his own ſoul to be good, and do good; and therefore will ſpend himſelf in theſe endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, though no body will pay him, no nor thank him for it. Mark the different temper that was in Chriſt, and ſome of his followers: they ſerved God for meat and drink, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 26. but he accounted it his meat and drink to ſerve him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 34.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:38039:46"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>God is all to the godly man in his Sufferings. An account of Self-ſufferers, Papiſts and others. God is All to the godly man in the Efficient, the Material and Final cauſe of his ſufferings, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained. God is all to the godly man in his manner of fearing Afflictions and Perſecutions.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>4. GOD is <hi>All</hi> to the godly man in his <hi>Sufferings.</hi> I know that unſound and hypocritical ſpirits are much more forward to do than ſuffer; and yet no doubt the power of ſelf-love and affectation of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, without any higher princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, may prepare and prompt men to endure Perſecution: And it need no
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:38039:46"/> more be wondred at, that the meer animal and ſelfiſh life ſhould expoſe it ſelf to much ſmart, and many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities, than that a generous Cock ſhould fight to crow, and expoſe himſelf to death it ſelf, to get the victory over his Antagoniſt. It is well known how much the ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Papiſts will deny, and debaſe, and degrade, and torment them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, what Penances and Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, and poverty they will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go: and all this out of a ſlaviſh fear of God, and a deſign to keep their luſts alive: They will half kill their own bodies, rather than crucifie their luſts, or mortifie the body of ſin: Theſe things they do, not for the mortification of luſts, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed theſe things they do rather than they will mortifie them, for theſe things with them ſupply the place of Mortification: But I fear we have many <hi>Self-ſufferers</hi> in the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:38039:47"/> World, that will not own them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be of that Society. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it is a malicious reproach that is by ſome caſt upon the generality of Proteſtant ſufferers at this day in the World, <hi>viz.</hi> that they ſuffer for humour and ſelf-conceit, out of obſtinacy, and a ſpirit of contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, for applauſe and a greater cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboration of their party: But yet it may reaſonably be feared, that there are too many that do ſo. It ſeems not at all ſtrange to me, that a man ſhould ſtudy <hi>Self-advancement</hi> by a pretended <hi>Self-denial,</hi> that he ſhould ſeem to loſe his life, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that he may <hi>find</hi> it, I mean that he ſhould pretend to crucifie the meer animal and ſelfiſh life, on purpoſe to enjoy it the more ſecurely, and hug it the more dearly; that a man ſhould take joyfully the ſpoiling of his Goods, rather than violate his fleſhly intereſt, or expoſe his luſts to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:38039:47"/> ſpoil. Men do ſometimes moſt of all maintain and pamper this dying life of theirs, when they ſeem to ſtarve it; and drive on the ſame deſign with <hi>Judas,</hi> even when their Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſeem to be the ſame with <hi>Pauls.</hi> Men may as verily feel themſelves, and as paſſionately pleaſe themſelves in the ſeeming conſtancy, courage and patience of their ſufferings, as in the pretended zeal and devotion of their actions; and as truly ſeek and ſet up themſelves, and a <hi>Self-ſupremacy</hi> in their own ſouls, by the one as by the other.</p>
                     <p>But God is <hi>All</hi> to the truly godly ſoul in his <hi>Perſecutions.</hi> This I might explain as to the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of them, the <hi>End</hi> of them, and the <hi>Manner</hi> of ſuſtaining them. As to the <hi>efficient cauſe</hi> of them, he does not fret, and ſtorm, and rage at men, whether open Enemies or falſe Friends, whether <hi>Informers, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers,</hi>
                        <pb n="74" facs="tcp:38039:48"/> 
                        <hi>Law-givers, Executioners;</hi> but he looks higher, and ſees and owns the hand of <hi>God</hi> in all things that befal him by the miniſtry of men. <hi>David</hi> knew that <hi>Shimei</hi> could not have curſed him, if God had not opened his mouth, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. 10. And our Saviour preſently replies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Pilate,</hi> when he bragged of his power, <hi>Joh.</hi> 19. 11. <hi>Thou couldſt have no power at all againſt me, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it were given thee from above.</hi> As to the <hi>material cauſe,</hi> or matter of his Perſecutions, God is all in that too: For he ſuffers for righteouſneſs ſake, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 10. and for well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 17. not for toyes and trifles, petty perſwaſions and private opinions, or matters of meer indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency. His ſoul is employed about more ſubſtantial and important mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; he will not ſo much as go to Law about ſuch things, much leſs expoſe himſelf to the rigour of a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:38039:48"/> Law for them; he will not ſo much as <hi>be in a heat</hi> about them, much leſs will he burn for them. And therefore it is not out of pride, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, or ſullenneſs (as the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors do ſlanderouſly report) but out of conſcience towards God that he endures grief, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 19. He knows no intereſt but that of his ſoul, which conſiſts in his moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act conformity to truth and holineſs; and it is to this intereſt, and the propagation of it that he is well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſacrifice whatever elſe may be reckoned dear or grateful to him.</p>
                     <p>As to the <hi>End</hi> of his ſufferings God is <hi>All</hi> unto the godly ſoul here too. There are many baſe, and low, and ſelfiſh ends, which a man may propound to himſelf in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for a good cauſe, which it were too long to inſiſt upon: All which the truly Divine ſoul abhors. He is not ſo prodigal of his <hi>blood,</hi> as to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:38039:49"/> ſhed one drop of it to purchaſe a name written in <hi>Red Letters;</hi> he will not expoſe his Goods to <hi>ſpoil</hi> in order to a more ample <hi>reſtitution;</hi> he will not <hi>fall</hi> on purpoſe to <hi>rebound</hi> the higher; nor have his perſon <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined,</hi> that ſo his name may <hi>ſpread,</hi> and his credit be <hi>enlarged.</hi> But he is well content to be <hi>reproached,</hi> that ſo God may be honoured; and to be <hi>ſtarved</hi> that truth may be <hi>maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> he is content to <hi>wither</hi> in his eſtate, that ſo he may <hi>flouriſh</hi> in g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ace, to <hi>periſh</hi> in the outward man, that he may be <hi>renewed</hi> in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; to die for the people, if ſo he may preſerve them from periſhing. The glory of God and the Salvation of ſouls, or if you will in plainer terms, the exerciſe of grace, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of truth, the advancement of the Kingdom of Chriſt in his own ſoul, and the propagation of it in the ſouls of others, are the grand de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:38039:49"/> of the godly ſoul, when he takes up any croſs.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, God is <hi>All</hi> to the godly ſoul in the manner of his ſuffering Perſecutions. His way of ſuſtaining them is with a pure, peaceable, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſelf-denying, patient, conſtant, chearful and charitable mind, a mind prepared to wiſh good, and do good to his very enemies and Perſecutors, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 44. In which excellent tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per he feels not, he pleaſes not, he enjoies not himſelf, or any ſelf-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, but glorifies God who gives ſuch power unto men, and admires Divine grace in that Heroical and moſt Chriſt-like paſſive frame which he finds derived into his ſoul. I ſhall wave the farther proſecution of this particular, becauſe I foreſee it will fall fitly alſo under another Head.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:38039:50"/>
                     <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>God is all to the godly man in his Enjoyments. What are the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments of Mind, of Body, of Eſtate. The unregenerate mind enjoyes all theſe in a ſenſual or ſelfiſh manner: But the godly man taſtes a Divine ſweetneſs in every thing that he enjoies; though there be different degrees of refinement in Souls that are refined. God is All to the godly Soul in his Endowments. The unregenerate mind, groſs in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring his own and other mens excellencies. The godly ſoul en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titles God to all that is good in himſelf or others. God is the All of a good man's life, and yet</hi>
                        <pb n="79" facs="tcp:38039:50"/> 
                        <hi>he is not ſatisfied with what he enjoies of him here, but perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually thirſts for more. The Doctrine to be underſtood with three cautions, that are briefly laid down</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>5. GOD is <hi>All</hi> to the godly man in his <hi>Enjoyments.</hi> The enjoyments of men in this World are manifold; it is impoſſible to run <hi>thorough</hi> them all paticularly. They may be reduced according to the old diviſion, unto three kinds, <hi>animi, corporis,</hi> and <hi>fortunae.</hi> The enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the <hi>mind</hi> are ſuch as theſe, peace, comfort, experiences of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine aſſiſtance, conqueſt of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and victory over ſpiritual ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; beſides the gifts and graces of the mind which are rather endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments than enjoyments, and will fall more directly under the next Head.</p>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:38039:51"/>
                     <p> Thoſe of the <hi>body</hi> are ſuch as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to the maintaining, adorning, feeding, cloathing, refreſhing of the body. Of the Third ſort are riches, honours, peace, victory, flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Families, gainful trading, and more of the like nature. All which the unregenerate mind loves and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyes in a groſs and unſpiritual man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>viz.</hi> either in a way meerly ſenſual and brutiſh, or elſe ſelfiſh and Idolatrous. Theſe Swine feed upon husks, reſt upon the loweſt round of the Ladder, and dwell upon the dark ſide of every creature: They know not the love of God, taſte not his ſweetneſs, admire not his perfection and image ſhining forth and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſting it ſelf in all created good.</p>
                     <p>But the godly man taſtes another kind of ſweetneſs, even the Divine goodneſs in every thing that he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyes. It is the ſtamp and impreſſion of God, <hi>viz.</hi> of his love and image
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:38039:51"/> which indeed gives the value to and puts the price upon every creature. Have you not known ſome men put a high eſteem upon a ſmall piece of Silver that bears the image of their Prince, or teſtifies the love of their friend? Why even ſo it is here. It is a derivative ſweetneſs, goodneſs and amiableneſs, which commends the creature to a judicious palate. There is almoſt as much difference between man and man, in the way of enjoying of things, as between men eating of the Fruit, and Swine devouring the husks, men picking out the marrow, and Dogs gnawing of the bones. All godly ſouls are not indeed alike refined, as we may ſhew hereafter. <hi>Iſaac</hi> loves his ſon <hi>Eſau</hi> too much for his <hi>Veniſon (Gen.</hi> 25. 28.) though his father <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> loved him for the <hi>Promiſe</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> ſake: And yet all ſuch ſouls are ſo far exalted and reſtored
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:38039:52"/> by grace to an underſtanding of their own dignity and happineſs, that they cannot poſſibly live and feed upon any thing below God himſelf.</p>
                     <p>6. God is <hi>All</hi> to the godly man in his <hi>Endowments,</hi> the <hi>All</hi> of what he is, as well as of what he hath. I have in part ſhewed already how prophanely the wicked man magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth himſelf in his wiſdom, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, ſtrength, and all other endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of body and mind. To which I might add, that he is alſo very groſs in admiring the endowments of other men, and the ſeveral excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies that are in other creatures. The barbarous people of the Iſland <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lita</hi> ſeemed to be more devout in this reſpect than the incraſſated <hi>Jews:</hi> they when they ſaw how miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly <hi>Paul</hi> was endowed, concluded it was ſomething Divine in him; only they put it into an ill phraſe, for they ſaid that he was a God,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:38039:52"/> 
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 28. 6. But theſe ſtand ſtaring at <hi>Peter,</hi> as if they thought that he by his own power or holineſs, had wrought ſuch wonders, <hi>Act</hi> 3. Oh how are the underſtandings and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of natural men capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated, confined and terminated in poor particularities!</p>
                     <p>But the godly and renewed ſoul, eyes and loves the excellencie of God ſhining forth in all accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and endowments, whether his own or any other creatures: In all theſe he ſees another kind of beauty than the wicked man takes notice of. As he owns God in all that he doth, performeth, poſſeſſeth, ſo he enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles him to all that he is. He him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is not wiſe, juſt, humble, holy in mind, nor ſtrong, beautiful or excellent in body; but God is All this in him. The flattering Ruler looks upon Chriſt, but as a meer man, and yet aſcribes goodneſs to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:38039:53"/> him, <hi>Good Maſter,</hi> &amp;c. But our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour leads up his thoughts to the Fountain, <hi>None is good but God.</hi> The Jews wonder how Chriſt came by all that learning; but he preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolves them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7. 16. <hi>My Doctrine is not mine, but his that ſent me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In a word, God is the <hi>All</hi> of a good man's life; In whom he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joies it, in whom alone it is ſweet, for whom he ſpends it, and for whoſe ſake alone he is content to prolong it; reckoning with his Lord and Saviour that he came not into the World to ſerve himſelf, or to ſeek his own glory, but the glory of him that ſent him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7. 18. God is ſo All to him, as the ſoul is to the body, <hi>Tota in toto &amp; tota in quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet parte,</hi> wholly in his ſoul and in all the faculties of it, wholly in his life and in all the paſſages thereof.</p>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:38039:53"/>
                     <p> God is ſo All to him that he is not ſatisfied with him neither, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he may enjoy more of him, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he may enjoy all of him that is to be enjoyed by a creature of ſuch a capacity. He aſpires after this perfection, to know, nor love, nor enjoy nothing but God in the World: He labours to attain to the very Reſurrection of the dead whilſt he is yet alive, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 11. that is, to ſuch a pure, perfect and Divine Life, as the Children of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection ſhall be advanced to.</p>
                     <p>And now underſtand all that I have ſaid with theſe Cautions.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. This is principally to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of Good men, grown up to ſome perfection of Stature. You ſee already, and may further ſee that it is exactly true of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and and that it is alſo true of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and other eminent ſervants of God. But we know that there are
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:38039:54"/> alſo babes in Chriſt, ſpiritual men that are yet in a great meaſure car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 1. That mighty Spirit of <hi>Jeſus</hi> that ſits as a Refiner of Silver in the ſouls of men, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines them by degrees; and yet is content that thoſe ſhould be called pure, in whom yet much droſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. It only holds of good men when they are themſelves, when they are in their right ſpiritual wits, of good men when they act upon deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when they are free from tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, dejections, paſſions, diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances. For there is a ſeaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in even the <hi>wiſe Virgins</hi> do ſlumber, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 5. wherein even the Spouſe of Chriſt, who was all fair and ſpotleſs, is ſecure and careleſs, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. There was a ſeaſon when good <hi>Joſiah</hi> fought his own battel, and not the Lords; when good <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> magnified himſelf, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:38039:54"/> in his own Treaſures, more than in the magnificence of God; when holy <hi>David</hi> himſelf reſolved to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice the lives of innocents to his own luſts, and to avenge a quarrel of his own, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
                     <p n="3">3. This is only to be underſtood of regenerate perſons, ſo far as they are regenerate: In <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf there remained ſomething that was unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, perverſe and rebellious, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. though he will not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that it was he himſelf, <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. Every regenerate and true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſoul, ſo far as he is regenerate and acteth up to the height of Divine principles, doth thus ſee, taſte, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, and deſign God in all, as I have ſhewed. For the very life and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Religion is the <hi>dethroning of Self</hi> and <hi>advancing of God into preeminence.</hi> In as much therefore as God being ſupreme and his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:38039:55"/> prevailing in a ſoul, is the very life and ſoul of Religion; it will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily follow that the Doctrine holds good concerning every truly regenerate ſoul, and that every ſuch ſoul hath this temper as to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominancy of it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:38039:55"/>
                     <head>CHAP. X. <hi>The improvement of the Doctrine laid down by way of examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. A general direction what Queries men are to put to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as to the finding out of this matter. Certain inſtances of a Self-emptied and God-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting mind. The firſt inſtance, When we are concerned in all the wickedneſs committed in the World as truly as if it were committed by our ſelves. The ſecond, when we are more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the iniquity of an action, than the injury that is done to our ſelves thereby.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>YOU cannot but by this time be ſomewhat in love with this excellent and Angel-like temper,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:38039:56"/> and deſirous to find whether you your ſelves be thus ſpirited. It is doubtleſs a ſcrutiny and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion becoming the moſt ſerious and generous minds: For all Religion is reduced to this <hi>ſumma Totalis;</hi> and Religion is the only concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſouls. Examine therefore I pray you, and that not only once and generally, but frequently and preciſely, and rifle into all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and (if it be poſſible) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the individual motions and actions of your hearts and lives to find this Divine temper; Examine your ſelves in all the forementioned particulars, whether God be <hi>All</hi> to you in your <hi>Apprehenſions, Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Actions, Sufferings, Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Endowments.</hi> Enquire whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the truth of God be dearer to you than your own party or perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; whether the intereſt of God lie nearer to your heart than ſelf-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:38039:56"/> the intereſt of your own cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and reputation, whether the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the Divine Life be more deſireable to you than Self-accommodation or Self-advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; whether the love of God, or the naked poſſeſſion of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture do moſt delight you in every enjoyment; whether the Image of God, or your own, do moſt affect you in your Children; whether the glory of God, or your own, do moſt ſpirit you in your Actions; whether you be rent from Self-en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment, and centred upon God alone; whether you be emptied of Self-will, and molded into the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Will; whether you abound in your own ſenſe and Self-feeling, or be filled with the fullneſs of God; In a Word, whether all Self-love, and Self-ſupremacy be thrown down, and God alone do exerciſe his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty over all the powers of your
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:38039:57"/> ſouls. Theſe are very ſubſtantial enquiries. For your better diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, I will therefore propound to you ſome certain marks or ſigns of ſuch a Self-emptied and God-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting mind, as I have been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending; which yet indeed are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther branches and inſtances of it than ſigns.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>When we take our ſelves to be concerned in all the wickedneſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the World, as truly as if it were committed by our ſelves or our relations;</hi> I mean ſo far as to be grieved for it. We are wont to be dejected by reaſon of any groſs ſin, that we our ſelves fall into; this I do not condemn, nay judge ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary as our Duty; and yet this may poſſibly ariſe from a meer ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious principle, and may be found ſpringing up in the heart of a ſlave. We are apt to be troubled when our Children or near friends prove un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracious
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:38039:57"/> or openly rebellious againſt God; this I do not ſimply condemn neither, and yet I muſt tell you, that this may ariſe from a meer na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural affection and a principle that is carnal. But if the intereſt of God lay ſo cloſe and warm to our hearts as it ought to do, and as it does to the Saints and Angels in Heaven, we ſhould mourn over the ſins of all men, even our Enemies and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, as truly as our friends; we ſhould be grieved for the Apoſtaſie of mankind, yea, and of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils themſelves. The predominan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Religion in the ſoul would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine natural affections into ſpiritual, and exalt particular affections into univerſals. You have heard of a man who vexed his ſoul with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly converſations of ſtrangers, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 7. and of another, who when ever he lookt abroad and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held tranſgreſſours, was grieved,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:38039:58"/> 
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 158. And I have known a man, who when he lookt upon an Aſſembly of ignorant and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical and ungodly men, either in a Church or in a Market, would have wept over them, as if they had all been his own Family. It is an argument of God's ſupremacy in the ſoul, when we mourn over ſin becauſe it is a degeneracy from the pure nature of God, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is found in them whom we love or are related to.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>When in the wrongful perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions committed againſt us, we can look through our own injury, and be moſtly affected with the wickedneſs of the action.</hi> I do not ſay it is unlawful to be ſenſible of, or affected with the injury and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence offered to us: But I ſay it is no more than is common to a <hi>Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> or <hi>Harlot;</hi> no more than what is common to an Elephant, a Lion,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:38039:58"/> or a Dog, as well as to us; and therefore though it be a lawful thing and neceſſary, yet it is no great thing. But when we can look upon the reproaches caſt upon our names, and have our hearts mainly concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Name and Honour of God; when we can forget the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of our own fetters, and as it were not feel the ſmart of our own ſtripes and wounds, becauſe of the greater load and pain which we ſuſtain by the luſts of men that do inflict them, it is certainly an excellent inſtance of God's ſupremacy in our ſouls. But you will ſay, Is this poſſible? Is it poſſible that the ſoul, whilſt it is em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodied, ſhould be more concerned for God, than for its own body? I muſt confeſs it is ſomewhat diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, and very rare: Men complain of the <hi>Injuriouſneſs</hi> of men, but ſeldom of their <hi>Unrighteouſneſs;</hi> of the cruelty of their enemies as it
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:38039:59"/> is exerciſed upon them, but not as it is a departure from the holy and loving nature of God. But yet it is not impoſſible neither, thus to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the ſmarting of our own fleſh and carnal intereſt, in compariſon of the intereſt of truth and holineſs and the glory of God. For thus did our bleſſed Saviour, who ſeemed to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get his own pangs upon the Croſs, in compariſon of the ſin of them that Crucified him, praying, <hi>Father for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them, for they know not what they do,</hi> Luk. 23. 34. And that I may not ſeem to over-ſhoot you with Examples, thus did <hi>Stephen</hi> a man of like infirmities with us, whoſe laſt and loudeſt voice was, <hi>Lord lay not this ſin to their Charge, Act.</hi> 7. <hi>ult.</hi> as if his <hi>heart</hi> were more broken with the <hi>ſin,</hi> than his <hi>body</hi> bruiſed with the <hi>Stones</hi> of them that perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted him: Thus did <hi>Moſes,</hi> and thus did <hi>David,</hi> whoſe zeal and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:38039:59"/> againſt his enemies was princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally upon the account of their ſin, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 139. <hi>My zeal hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed me, becauſe mine enemies have forgotten thy Words.</hi> Upon which words <hi>Mollerus</hi> gloſſes thus, <hi>David in ſuis aerumnis non tam af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficitur malorum ſuorum ſenſu &amp; pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatis injuriis, quàm quòd videt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Dei ab hoſtibus contumeliâ affici.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:38039:60"/>
                     <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Three more Inſtances of a God exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mind. When in the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that befal us we can over-look all creature comforts and delight in the Will of God. When we repent of ſin and hate it for its own ſake, and eſteem nothing worſe than it is. When we take pleaſure in the gifts and graces of God ſhining forth in others as well as in our ſelves.</hi> Joſhua <hi>and</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah <hi>taxed. This temper proved to be Angelical.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>3. <hi>WHen in the Afflictions that befal us more immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the hand of God, we can over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look</hi>
                        <pb n="99" facs="tcp:38039:60"/> 
                        <hi>all the creature-comforts which are taken from us, and kiſs the hand of God that takes them.</hi> There is all reaſon that the Will of God ſhould be dearer to us than any created good, however our fond and ſenſual hearts may contradict and blaſpheme. Is not the Will of God to be ſeen in all our croſſes, loſſes, ſickneſſes, in all our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal, domeſtical and national diſturbances? And is not even this Will of God, God himſelf? Is it not infinitely wiſe, holy and perfect? What are our ſorry, ſcant, mixt enjoyments then in this World, that they ſhould be valued againſt this Almighty and Sacred pleaſure? We magnifie the good Will and pleaſure of God in our peace, plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, health, proſperity; and it is good to do ſo in a right ſpiritual manner: But poſſibly it may be the ſweetneſs of the enjoyments them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:38039:61"/> that we do ſo much reliſh, and not the good Will of God in them. But if in the ſharpeſt and ſoreſt afflictions that do befall us, we find our ſelves ſo maſtered and over-powered with the ſenſe of the purity and perfection of the Will of God, that we can adore and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence it, yea cleave to it and love it more than any of our creature comforts, more than our lives them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves nakedly conſidered, it is an excellent inſtance of that ſoveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which God hath obtained in our ſouls. This was the temper of our bleſſed Saviour, who ſeemed ſcarce to taſte the bitterneſs of the Cup, for the excellency of the hand that reached it to him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 18. 11. <hi>The Cup which my Father hath given me ſhall I not drink it.</hi> The afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the Lord ſendeth, ſhall I not bear it, ſaies old <hi>Eli,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. 18. <hi>It is the Lord let him do what</hi>
                        <pb n="101" facs="tcp:38039:61"/> 
                        <hi>ſeemeth him good.</hi> The Book which was given to the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> to eat, was as ſweet as Honey to him, becauſe it was given him by the hand of God, although it contained no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it but <hi>lamentation and mourning, and woe,</hi> Ezek. 2. 10. 3. 3. the Will of God was pleaſant and delightful to him: for though the contents thereof were grievous, yet he gladly aſſented to the end and ſcope of theſe providences, as the Dutch Annotators gloſs upon the words.</p>
                     <p>4. <hi>When we eſteem nothing worſe than ſin is, for which we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of it or hate it.</hi> You may fright ſuperſtitious minds by telling them of judgements and puniſhments, and ſcare hypocrites with everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing burning: but certainly there is that in the very nature of ſin, that is more dreadful to an ingenuous ſoul, than fire and brimſtone can fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:38039:62"/> Such a ſoul cannot ſin without pain; he eſteems ſin to be the very ſame to his ſoul, which a diſeaſe is to the body; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is not ſo properly ſaid to be grieved for it (which ſeems to reſpect the evil conſequences of it) as indeed to be ſick of it, as one is of a diſtemper, or weary of it, as one is of a painful burden. It is well when men will reform their evil waies for fear of the puniſhments of this World, or the Hell of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (though I fear ſuch reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is rather ſuperſtition than true converſion in God's account:) but it were much better if men would be <hi>drawn</hi> to God, and not <hi>driven</hi> to him. Perhaps the fear of wrath and Hell may at length end in a more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous and generous temper; but for the preſent it ſeems to me to be nothing elſe but a ſpirit of bondage: when <hi>Iſaac</hi> is once grown up in the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:38039:62"/> ſoul, this Bond-woman and her ſon muſt pack; <hi>Love when it is perfected will caſt out fear,</hi> 1 Joh. 4. 18.</p>
                     <p>5. <hi>When we can rejoyce and take pleaſure in the gifts and graces of God ſhining forth in others, as hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily and really as in our ſelves.</hi> It were to be wiſhed that we could do it as much: but this is a rare attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and for ought I know, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for the other World. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever if we do it as truly and really, it is an argument, that God is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than ſelf in our ſouls. <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> though a good man, being tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with zeal for his Maſter's credit fail'd in this, when he was offended at the gift of Prophecie confer'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad,</hi> and cry'd, <hi>My Lord Moſes forbid them,</hi> Num. 11. 28. And it lies as a blemiſh to this day upon <hi>Jonah</hi> the Prophet, that he valued his own reputation above the kindneſs of God ſhewed
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:38039:63"/> upon the poor <hi>Ninevites.</hi> We profeſs to diſreliſh this temper in <hi>Joſhuah</hi> and <hi>Jonah;</hi> but (alas) we are apt to indulge it in our ſelves. For where ſhall we find a ſoul ſo emptied of it ſelf, and ſo raviſhed with the Divine beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and glory, that can be hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly well pleaſed with the temporal proſperity of others, when it ſeems to jar with our own, or the beam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings forth of Divine luſtre upon the ſouls of others, when we our ſelves come to be eclipſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. If God were ſo ſupreme in our ſouls as he ought to be, we ſhould overlook our ſelves; look upon the excellencies of other men without diſdain or envy, yea, and admire and delight in the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications of God to our fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creatures, as heartily as if our own particular Beings were adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with them. Certainly there is
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:38039:63"/> no ſuch thing as <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> amongſt the Inhabitants of the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per World, but God is <hi>All in All</hi> unto them: and we commonly ſay, that one part of the happineſs of Heaven will be, that there will be no place for envy and emulation; From whence I infer, that thoſe ſouls that are in this World moſt refined and univerſaliz'd, have moſt of Heaven come into them, and do moſt plentifully taſte the Firſt-fruits of Eternal Life. This hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly temper we find in <hi>Moſes,</hi> made manifeſt in his anſwer to <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> Numb. 11. 29. In his Father-in-law <hi>Jethro,</hi> who rejoyced for all the goodneſs that the Lord had done to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Exod. 18. 9. In the Apoſtles who glorified God, and were right glad, becauſe that unto the Gentiles alſo God had granted Repentance unto Life, <hi>Act.</hi> 11. 18. And in Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> who
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:38039:64"/> is reported to have ſpoke thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Luther, Lutherus eſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus Dei ſervus, etiamſi me diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum millies mille vocaverit.</hi> It is an excellent ſign of Self-debaſement, and the exaltation of God in the ſoul, when propriety ceaſeth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:38039:64"/>
                     <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>The ſixth Inſtance an Univerſal Love. The notion of the love of the Brethren examined. Who is our Brother according to the Apoſtle</hi> James. <hi>No man can be truly ſaid to love God, who does not love the Image of God. The ſpirit of ſome men, even in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences to the love of God, is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Deviliſh than Divine. To be content that men ſhould go to Hell, implies a contentment that men ſhould be wicked, which is againſt the Honour of God. The ſeventh Inſtance, an holy unſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiedneſs with all the Attainments of this Life. It is an Argument of a mercenary and penurious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi>
                        <pb n="108" facs="tcp:38039:65"/> 
                        <hi>to be only deſirous to know the loweſt degree of ſaving Grace. To take up our reſt in Evidences deſtroies the nature of thoſe Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences. The Concluſion is an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to men to endeavour to make God All to themſelves, to which they are briefly moved and directed.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>6. <hi>AN Univerſal Love, a Love of the whole Creation;</hi> If we love all men, ſome with a love of <hi>delight,</hi> others with a love of <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion,</hi> it is an excellent argument of God's ſupremacy, yea of his <hi>All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> in our Affections: For it muſt needs be for God's ſake, if our Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity be thus large. Many men do mightily pleaſe themſelves with this, that they love the Brethren; though in the mean time they can well allow themſelves to hate all,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:38039:65"/> whom themſelves are pleaſed to eſteem otherwiſe: But I ſay unto you (ſaith Love it ſelf) <hi>Love your Enemies,</hi> Mat. 5. 44. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more a-kin to the nature of God, than a mind thus unbounded in its Charity and Benevolence, <hi>verſ.</hi> 45. Men boaſt much of their love of God: why <hi>no man hath ſeen God at any time</hi> (ſaies the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 12.) only he hath copied out himſelf in the Creation: and if we love not that, it is abſurd to talk of loving him: as if a man ſhould brag that he lov'd an <hi>Univerſal,</hi> when in the mean time he hateth all the <hi>particulars</hi> through which that Univerſal derives it ſelf. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks much of loving our Brother: but would you know who is this brother? he deſcribes him in the 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 20. <hi>His Brother whom he hath ſeen;</hi> which muſt not be underſtood, as if our love were to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:38039:66"/> be limited to them only whom we have actually ſet our eyes upon; but rather it is to be extended to every man that may be ſeen, <hi>q. d. Omne viſibile eſt amabile.</hi> All particular loves are capable of being defiled; yea the love of good men may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be a bad, that is, a ſelfiſh love: But when we find our hearts formed into an univerſal love of mankind, it is a ſign that God is principally concern'd in our hearts; for all men are not in themſelves lovely, nor obliging to us. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but wonder that ever men ſhould imagine that they are then moſt loving of God, and mightily zealous for him, when they moſt rage againſt his enemies, curſe them, kill them, and devote them to deſtruction, and alledge <hi>David</hi>'s Prophecies to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their Imprecations. Shall I ſay concerning theſe men, as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to his Diſciples, they know
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:38039:66"/> not what ſpirit they are of? Truly one may much ſuſpect it to be <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh,</hi> becauſe it is <hi>envious, bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wrongful, cenſerious</hi> and <hi>dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning;</hi> rather than <hi>Divine,</hi> which is <hi>pure, peaceable, gentle, eaſie to be entreated, full of mercy,</hi> &amp;c. However, ſure I am that the wrath of man worketh not the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 20. God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give our haſty and raſh paſſions! But to be in cold blood well content that any man ſhould go to Hell, is a ſad ſign that ones ſelf is not in the way to Heaven, nor ſpirited according to God: For God is Love, and deſires not the death of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but wills all men to be ſaved, and to come unto the knowledge of the truth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 4. God's glory is indeed the communication and beaming forth of himſelf unto the creature; he is then <hi>honoured,</hi> when he is <hi>imitated;</hi> ſin and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:38039:67"/> is only contrary to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, as darkneſs alone is contrary to light. Yea to be content that men ſhould go to Hell, implies a contentment that men ſhould be wicked: For it is wickedneſs alone that brings men to Hell; nay indeed to be wicked is to be in Hell.</p>
                     <p>7. <hi>An holy unſatisfiedneſs with all things here below, yea with the very gracious attainments of this life, and an eager panting after a ſtate of perfection in God.</hi> It is an argument of a mercenary ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and a ſign that men look upon Eternal Life rather as a <hi>Bargain,</hi> than their proper <hi>happineſs,</hi> when they are only deſirous to know the <hi>loweſt degree</hi> of ſaving grace, and would go to Heaven at the cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt rate. When men do deſire to find evidences of grace in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, on purpoſe that they may
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:38039:67"/> take up their reſt in them and fix there, it is a ſign of a penurious, ſhrivelled and parſimonious mind; and in ſo doing, they do <hi>ipſo facto</hi> deſtroy the nature of theſe evidences. The ſureſt evidence of grace is that which ſprings up in the ſoul it ſelf, and diſcovers it ſelf in the growth of true goodneſs, and in reſtleſs motions after God. He that can be content with any meaſure of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs that is competible to man in this earthly mixed ſtate, content to live an eternity in this kind of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, yea though he could do it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin, hath not ſuch honourable thoughts of God as he ought to have. But when the ſoul is unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with all its preſent acquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and attainments, and ſprings up inceſſantly into God, and the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and fuller reſemblance of him, and into a ſtate of perfect purity (as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.)
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:38039:68"/> it is a certain argument and inſtance of an abſolute ſupremacy that God hath obtained in ſuch a ſoul. And truly I cannot reckon that God is ſo great in my eye, nor ſo high in my heart as he ought to be, till I arrive at this temper.</p>
                     <p>To Conclude then, <hi>Labour to make God All things to your ſelves,</hi> according to all the fore-named in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, <hi>viz.</hi> in your Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Affections, Actions, Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Enjoyments, Endowments, to be abſtracted as much as can be from all poor, pinching particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities. And now, ſhall I need to tell you that <hi>this is the moſt noble and Angelical Life?</hi> You your ſelves ſurely know that that which makes the life of Saints and Angels ſo much happier and more glorious than ours, is, that they are not ſunk into any ſenſes nor drowned in any matter, but are perfectly centred upon
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:38039:68"/> God and filled with him. Shall I need to tell you, that <hi>thus we ſhall live in that other World,</hi> to which we all hope to come; or that <hi>this will be to us</hi> (not only an infallible evidence, but indeed) <hi>a real begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of that bleſſed Life?</hi> I hope I need not inſiſt upon ſuch motives.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Be often preſſing upon your ſelves the vanity, emptineſs, inſufficiency and unſuitableneſs of all created good.</hi> Self and the creature muſt be nothing in our eye, before God can be All things in it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Conſider well the worth of your own Souls.</hi> Think of that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Angel-like capacity which God hath beſtowed upon them, which nothing but himſelf can fill up, and live not below the dignity of your own ſouls.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Meditate often upon Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> who lived to propound this way of living, and both lived and died to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:38039:69"/> it. Of his example you have heard already; ſee <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 34. 6. 38. 7. 16, 18. 9. 4. 12. 27, 28. 14. 24. 17. 4. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. 42. and many other places. And that he lived and died to purchaſe this bleſſed life for us, is plain, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 19. <hi>God was in Chriſt reconciling the world to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> The great end for which Chriſt came into the World and went out of it was, to reſtore the ſouls to God, who were fallen from him into ſelf and the creature; to reunite and reconcile us, and make us partakers of Divine fulneſs.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:38039:69"/>
                  <p> THE SPIRITUAL MAN IN A Carnal Fit: OR, The former Doctrine Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by its oppoſite, in a famous Inſtance from PSAL. LV. 6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. White,</hi> for <hi>Henry Mortlock</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, and at the <hi>White-Hart</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> 1678.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:38039:70"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:38039:70"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>PSAL.</hi> 55. 6. And I ſaid, O that I had wings like a Dove! for then would I flee away and be at reſt.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The meaning of the Words: The diviſion of the Verſe into its parts, with a gloſs upon each. The Propoſition contained in the Words. That the hearts of good men are ſometimes ſurprized with fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, impatience of troubles,</hi>
                        <pb n="120" facs="tcp:38039:71"/> 
                        <hi>and eager deſires of reſt from Adverſity. This proved by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, but moſt largely by the Example of</hi> David <hi>in this place, wherein the Emphaſis of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral words in the Text are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THis <hi>Pſalm</hi> contains a Prayer of <hi>David</hi> rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to himſelf, and his enemies. The Prayer that he puts up for himſelf, is for deliverance from his troubles, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1, 2. The occaſion of it is laid down, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3, 4, 5. and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6, 7, 8. It is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſuppoſed to be Penned by the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> in the time of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſecuted by <hi>Saul,</hi> when he was reduced into ſome eminent ſtrait. But what particular ſtrait it was that he was now in, is not
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:38039:71"/> certain. Some refer it to the time of his flight to <hi>Nob,</hi> which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. Others re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it to the time when he was conſpired againſt by <hi>Saul,</hi> and like to be betrayed by the men of <hi>Keilah,</hi> whom he had a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo much obliged; mentioned 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. But whenſoever it was, it is very clear that his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs was great, and himſelf rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſink under his burden. The words may poſſibly ſeem at firſt hearing to be the cry of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout mind, and an expreſſion of a raiſed temper. But if we look nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly into them, and ponder all the circumſtances, we ſhall find indeed that they are the voice of an impotent and impatient ſpirit, and do diſcover a great infirmity in this holy man, and are more elegant than devout, have more of <hi>Rhetorick</hi> in them than <hi>Divinity;</hi>
                        <pb n="122" facs="tcp:38039:72"/> like thoſe of <hi>Saul</hi> to the men of <hi>Ziph, Bleſſed be ye of the Lord, for ye have compaſſion on me:</hi> And what was this compaſſion, but their adminiſtring to his malicious and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful luſts?</p>
                     <p>In the Words there are Three Parts.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Optandi forma,</hi> a form of wiſhing, <hi>Oh that I had:</hi> In the Hebrew it is <hi>Mi jitten li,</hi> who will give me? which is their form of wiſhing, and not of doubting or deſpairing, as ſome through their ignorance of the Hebrew Idiom have imagined. This form of wiſhing is very uſual in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, which we Tranſlate ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by <hi>Oh that,</hi> as in <hi>Job</hi> 11. 5. 13. 5. <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. 1. <hi>Oh that mine head were waters!</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 53. ult. <hi>Oh that the Salvation of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael were come out of Zion!</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we Tranſlate it by <hi>Would</hi>
                        <pb n="123" facs="tcp:38039:72"/> 
                        <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. 67. <hi>In the morning thou ſhalt ſay, Would God it were even,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Judg.</hi> 9. 29. <hi>Would to God this people were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mine hand.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>Optationis materia,</hi> the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the wiſh, a wing like a Dove. <hi>Eber cajonah.</hi> He firſt laies down the matter of his wiſh, a <hi>wing;</hi> and then illuſtrates or amplifies it, <hi>as of a Dove,</hi> or <hi>like a Dove.</hi> It is ordinary in the Hebrew Idi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>om to put the ſingular number for the plural, and ſo it is here. And yet there may be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more in it too; in wiſhing for a wing and not wings, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly he deſcribes the great fear and haſte and paſſion that he was in. What a thirſt was that rich man in, when he expected ſo much relief from a drop of water, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. And what a fright was <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> in when he wiſhes ſo earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtly
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:38039:73"/> for one ſingle wing? The more inconſiderable and ſmall a thing is which one catches at, the greater argument is it of diſtreſs, fear and diſtraction of mind. If inſtead of the wing of a Dove, he had cried out for the feather of a Dove, it had been yet a more lively deſcription of his amazed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and indeed the Word here in the Text does ſignifie a Feather as well as a Wing; and ſo we Tranſlate it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. 13. <hi>Her Feathers with yellow Gold.</hi> But it is not any kind of Wing that will ſerve his turn; it muſt be like the Wing of a Dove, the ſwifteſt that he could think of, as we ſhall ſee by and by. Certainly it was a great fright of mind that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited this ſtrange wiſh: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſo he confeſſes in the fourth and fifth <hi>verſes,</hi> where he calls it <hi>pain,</hi> yea <hi>pain of heart, terrour,</hi>
                        <pb n="125" facs="tcp:38039:73"/> yea a <hi>terrour of death, fearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, trembling</hi> and <hi>horrour,</hi> yea a <hi>deluge of horrour.</hi> Here's juſt the <hi>heart</hi> of a ſilly Dove, that ſpies the Hawk and trembles and flies, and therefore it's fit it ſhould be matcht with <hi>Wings</hi> of the ſame, <hi>Oh that I had wings like a Dove.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Optati ſinis,</hi> the end of a thing wiſh'd for; that is twofold, <hi>Medius &amp; ultimus,</hi> I will <hi>fly away</hi> and <hi>be at reſt:</hi> he would ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſcape out of the dangers and troubles that he was in, and keep himſelf out of harms way for the time to come.</p>
                     <p>All the Divinity that I can pick up out of this elegant and pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical wiſh will be contained under this one Propoſition.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The hearts of good men are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſurprized with great fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, impatience of troubles, and</hi>
                        <pb n="126" facs="tcp:38039:74"/> 
                        <hi>eager deſire of reſt from Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Here are three thing to be ſpoke to, <hi>Fearfulneſs, Impatience of trouble,</hi> and <hi>eager deſire of reſt.</hi> The firſt of theſe is not indeed directly found in the Text, only it ſeems to be implied in the word <hi>Dove,</hi> which is <hi>Meticuloſa avis &amp; imbellis.</hi> And therefore I ſhall not ſpeak much diſtinctly to that, but to the two laſt. Only I cannot but intimate, that there is a vaſt difference between <hi>fearing</hi> of God and <hi>being afraid</hi> of him. To fear him is often made the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of an ingenuous holy, child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſpirit, and is therefore made the ſumm of all Religion, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 13. but to be afraid of him, to worſhip him as a ſevere <hi>numen</hi> or a <hi>ſaevus dominus,</hi> with a kind of horrour and invidiouſneſs of mind, with a ſecret kind of wrath
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:38039:74"/> and jealouſie or doubting, does certainly argue a ſuperſtitious and legal ſpirit, a mind that for the preſent is in bondage; yea if I miſtake not the meaning of the Prophet, he makes this the badge of an hypocritical people, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33. 14. <hi>Fearfulneſs hath ſurprized the Hypocrites: who amongſt us ſhall dwell with devouring fire; who amongſt us ſhall dwell with everlaſting burning?</hi> As ſoon as <hi>Adam</hi> had ſinned againſt God, he becomes afraid of him and flies from him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. And to this day men do ſecretly hate him whom they fear.</p>
                     <p>As for the fear of the creature and fear of trouble in the fleſh, it is a predominant principle in carnal minds where ſelf rules, but it is incident to the beſt of Saints, and is recorded as their infirmity for our caution; as in <hi>Iſaac, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi>
                        <pb n="128" facs="tcp:38039:75"/> 
                        <hi>Peter,</hi> who for fear of men, denied one his <hi>Wife,</hi> another his <hi>reaſon,</hi> a third his Saviour. But it is <hi>wearineſs of troubles,</hi> and <hi>eager deſires of reſt from Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,</hi> that are moſt plainly found in the Text, and which I am there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to ſpeak to. I think I need not ſpeak to them ſingly, for I think they are never found ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, but are inſeparable Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</p>
                     <p>And here I ſhall endeavour to ſhew that good men are ſubject to theſe diſtempers. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Shew the cauſe of the diſtemper. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Preſcribe the cure of it. And laſtly improve the Doctrine in ſome few Inferences.</p>
                     <p>That the hearts of good men are ſometimes ſurprized with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience of troubles and eager de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of reſt from Adverſity, will appear by the Examples of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:38039:75"/> eminent Saints. I will not peremptorily determine whether the Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> were thus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered, when he fled from the Perſecution raiſed againſt him by <hi>Jezabel,</hi> gat him all alone into the Wilderneſs, and <hi>requeſted for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that he might die,</hi> 1 King. 19. But I doubt not to affirm that holy <hi>Job</hi> was under this diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: He ſticks not to confeſs, that he is even tired out, and wearied, and waſted, and exhauſted in his ſpirits with the Afflictions that were upon him; <hi>Weariſome nights are appointed to me,</hi> Job 7. 3. <hi>My ſoul is weary of my life, it is bitter within me,</hi> Job 10. 1. Therefore you have him even cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the day and night of his birth almoſt through the Third Chapter; and wiſhing to be hid in the Grave over and over, and that with a great deal of vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:38039:76"/> 
                        <hi>Job</hi> 6. 8, 9, 10. <hi>O that I might have my requeſt: and that God would grant me the thing that I long for! Even that it would pleaſe God to deſtroy me, that he would let looſe his hand and cut me off.</hi> And the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> was wearied with the Perſecution and Oppreſſion of his Country-men, although the ſame was light in compariſon of what he was to ſuffer, <hi>Jer.</hi> 12. 5. he was wearied with running even with the Foot-men. At another time you have him alſo curſing his Birth-day through impatience, and the man that brought tidings of his coming into the World, becauſe he ſlew him not from the Womb, <hi>Jer.</hi> 20. 14, 15, 16, 17. The ſame Prophet could be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to live a ſolitary, unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, unprofitable life, like an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choret, ſo he might but eſcape
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:38039:76"/> the treachery of the people, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. 2. What a diſcontentment and paſſion <hi>Jonah</hi> was in, and that for a light matter, all know, and how he will needs be gone out of the World in a pet, his Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory does fully relate. Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>David</hi> and his impatience, diſquietneſs, wearineſs and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity of mind, I have many things to ſay, and the book of <hi>Pſalms</hi> does afford many pregnant inſtances: <hi>How long wilt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get me, O Lord, how long ſhall mine enemies exalt themſelves over me, how long ſhall the Adverſary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, how long ſhall the wicked triumph,</hi> &amp;c. But I need not go far from my Text to demonſtrate the greatneſs of <hi>David</hi>'s diſtemper. In the words of this Text, and the two following Verſes you will diſcern the greatneſs of his weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the eagerneſs of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:38039:77"/> of deliverance, if we conſider the following particulars.</p>
                     <p>1. In general, he ſeems to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend his caſe deſperate, out of which there was no eſcape. <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentur hae voces eſſe hominis deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rati,</hi> ſaies <hi>Mollerus.</hi> The Words of the Text ſeem to be rather a boyling up of paſſion, than the putting up of a Prayer, a wiſe or well grounded Prayer. This is a ſad diſtemper of mind, very diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable to God and unbeſeeming a godly ſoul; and yet ſo diſeaſed in his mind does <hi>David</hi> here ſeem to be; as alſo at other times: as when he forgot all the promiſes that God had made to him, and cry'd out, <hi>All men are Lyars,</hi> and <hi>I ſhall periſh by the hand of Saul.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>2. More particularly, he is ſo weary of his Perſecution, and ſo intent upon deliverance, that he
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:38039:77"/> puts God upon the working of Miracles for his eſcape, and ſuch a Miracle as we never read that he wrought for any man, <hi>Oh that I had wings!</hi> What, muſt the courſe of nature, and the order of the Creation be inverted for him? It was a devout and holy zeal in <hi>David</hi> to envy the Sparrows and the Swallows becauſe they were allowed to come nearer the Altar of God than he, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. 3. But to be content to be transformed into a ſilly Bird, meerly to have the benefit of her wings to eſcape a temporal danger, is certainly a ſtrange diſtraction in a holy man. Oh how wonderful great is the power of this animal life, which puts men upon ſuch ſtrange con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances for its own preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yea even ſuch men as in whom the reigning power of it is deſtroyed, and a higher life
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:38039:78"/> hath taken place! Certainly the wings of <hi>David</hi>'s Soul, the wings of Faith and hope were ſadly moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted away, or he would never have invented ſuch a ſtrange device, as a winged body.</p>
                     <p>He is ſo eager, that any kind of wings will not ſerve his turn neither, they muſt be wings of a <hi>Dove,</hi> the ſwifteſt that he could think of; <hi>Oh that I had wings like a Dove.</hi> For ſo I judge that he names the wings of a Dove rather than any other Bird, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the great ſpeedineſs of her flight; though I know ſome men to excuſe the Prophet, or rather indeed to ſhew their own wit, have invented other reaſons. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliſts ſpeak much of the ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Dove in flying, they ſay ſhe can out-fly the Hawk, and need not to fear him, if ſhe would but keep a direct and ſimple flight,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:38039:78"/> but when ſhe begins to clap with her wings in a certain kind of pride and wantonneſs, then ſhe becomes a prey.</p>
                     <p>4. Yea, ſo eager is he, that if he had ſuch wings, he would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently fly with them. He does not wiſh the wings of a Dove for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament and beauty, but for ſpeed; and if he had them he would not ſtand picking and dreſſing, and trimming them, as ſometimes Doves do, but he would preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpread his new ſails and be gone. We Tranſlate the words, <hi>Oh that I had wings like a Dove, for then would I flye away;</hi> but in the Hebrew, there is nothing between the wings of a Dove and flying with them: The words run thus, <hi>Oh that I had a wing like a Dove, I will flye away and be at reſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="136" facs="tcp:38039:79"/>
                     <p> 5. Yea, he would haſten with them. He would not ſimply fly with his wings, but uſe them to the utmoſt expedition: As if the wings of a Dove and flying with them were not enough, he will alſo haſten with them, he will fly as faſt as wings will carry him, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>I would haſten my eſcape from the Storm and Tempeſt;</hi> In which words he ſeems to continue his Metaphor, and to allude to the manner of Doves, who when they are abroad and preſage a Storm, make all poſſible ſpeed to recover their Cote.</p>
                     <p>6. So great is his impatience and eagerneſs, that he will be content to wander, to have no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain place, not to be fixt any where; ſo he may but eſcape; he cares not whither it is, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>Lo then would I wander,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <pb n="137" facs="tcp:38039:79"/>
                     <p> 7. He would be content to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der afar off; he cares not how far, as far as wings will carry him, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>Lo then would I wander afar off.</hi> He that uſed to be ſo loving of the Land, and ſo deſirous of the Sanctuary, that he was once ready to wiſh himſelf a <hi>Swallow</hi> or a <hi>Sparrow,</hi> that he might flye thither, now wiſhes himſelf a <hi>Dove</hi> that he might flie far enough from it, into ſome of the utmoſt parts of the earth. It was wont to be his Policy to abide in ſome of the borders of <hi>Judah,</hi> and to hover about the skirts of that Land, that ſo he might be ready to lay hold of any advantage that God ſhould put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hand for the obtaining of the Kingdom (as it is the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of moſt men, to contrive to dwell as near as they can to their hopes:) but now his hopes of a
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:38039:80"/> Kingdom are expired, and all his policys are expired with them, he is ſo eager to be got out of harms way, that he never thinks of being in the way of prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Lo then I would wander afar off.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>8. So impatient and eager is he, that he cares not though he reſted in a Wilderneſs, ſo he might but reſt. He that was wont to take ſo much delight in good compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as you may ſee in the 14 <hi>Verſ.</hi> of this <hi>Pſalm,</hi> can now be content to ſit down in a ſolitary Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, void of all humane Society. He that uſed to be ſo loving of the company of men, can now be content to converſe amongſt Beaſts in the Wilderneſs, and expoſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to their ſavage and ravenous temper. This ſeems indeed to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that the luſts of his enemies were grown to a great height of
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:38039:80"/> ſury and fierceneſs, when he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended it ſafer converſing with the Beaſts of the Wilderneſs than with them. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, as <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> uſed to ſay: But yet it argues the greatneſs of his diſtemper, who would be content with a life amongſt Beaſts, which is a moſt unprofitable life, ſcarce worthy to be called life, ſo he might but live at reſt. But may ſome ſay, he would have only retired into the Wilderneſs for a ſeaſon, he would have returned when the Storm was over. It ſeems other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to me, for,</p>
                     <p>9. He will be content not only to eſcape thither, but even to dwell there, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6. <hi>Eſchonah ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitabo,</hi> and <hi>Verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>Alin,</hi> I would <hi>remain</hi> in the Wilderneſs. He ſeems as if he would forget the promiſe of the Kingdom, and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:38039:81"/> all the hopes of it in an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Self-baniſhment. Now put all theſe together, and you will ſay with me, That here is an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of a good man in a very ſad diſtemper of Impatience of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and eager deſire of Reſt from Adverſity.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="141" facs="tcp:38039:81"/>
                     <head>CHAP. II. <hi>An enquiry into the cauſes of the foreſaid diſtemper in the minds of men. The firſt cauſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned,</hi> viz. <hi>A miſapprehenſion of the Nature of God, and a miſinterpretation of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences. A correction of theſe miſapprehenſions, and a preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of a cure in reference to this cauſe of the diſtemper.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AND now I will enquire what may be the cauſe of ſuch a diſeaſe as this in holy minds.
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:38039:82"/> Here I ſhall lay down ſome of the immediate cauſes as I apprehend, and for brevity ſake annex the cure to each, which is by taking away the cauſe.</p>
                     <p>The firſt Cauſe of this diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Impatience of troubles, and eager deſires of reſt from Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, is, a <hi>miſapprehenſion of the nature of God,</hi> and a <hi>miſinter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of His Providences.</hi> Men are apt to imagine God to be like unto themſelves, a peeviſh, ſelf-willed, Arbitrary Being, acting meerly by prerogative, or carried by paſſion, after the manner of ſome great King or Judge upon Earth. It is the miſery of theſe captive and degenerate ſouls of ours, that they are fain to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Notions and Ideas from men and their manner of acting and governing their petty Dominions,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:38039:82"/> whereby to apprehend and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of God, and his infinite na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and unſearchable Providences: and by this means we come to attribute thoſe things to God which indeed are utterly <hi>inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent</hi> with his perfect nature, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſame are found in thoſe earthly Potentates from whom we derive thoſe Ideas, and form theſe reſemblances. Now ſuch a God as we phancy to our ſelves muſt needs be burdenſome and grievous to us, eſpecially when he afflicteth us. Who would not vex, and fret, and rage under the Sentence of ſuch a Judge, as he ſuppoſed did command him to be puniſhed, meerly becauſe it was his pleaſure, or to ſhew his Authority, when there was no reaſon in the thing? Who can patiently bear the Yoke of ſuch
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:38039:83"/> a God, as does impoſe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands only <hi>Pro imperio,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict his puniſhments only <hi>Pro ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrio,</hi> only to ſhew his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity?</p>
                     <p>But ſuch is not the God whom we ſerve; All his Laws are the products of his Wiſdom and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite underſtanding, and not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon his Creatures till his own goodneſs and the good of the Creature was firſt conſulted: All his Providences are the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of Infinite Love and Benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and carried on by the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Laws of Righteouſneſs. If you would therefore poſſeſs your ſouls in patience, labour to purge your minds from imbittering thoughts of God, as if he did ſeek to get a name and make himſelf famous by the ſuffering of his Creatures, or were pleaſed
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:38039:83"/> with the ſighs and groans which his Almighty ſeverity can extort from thoſe whom he hath a mind to make miſerable. Be ye veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded that the Will of God, however abſolute and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited it is, doth alwaies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed according to the Eternal Rules of goodneſs and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: And this will heal your ſpirits of all fretfulneſs, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile your minds not only to thoſe Laws and Inſtitutions of his, which ſeem to be moſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary, but alſo to thoſe Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences which ſeem to be moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere or unequal.</p>
                     <p>By a like miſtake we are apt to aſcribe <hi>Paſſion</hi> to God, and to repreſent him to our ſelves as if he were all in a rage and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry angry, when he afflicts us. Which Notion deſtroies all that
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:38039:84"/> chearful acquieſcence under his hand, and that quiet and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly converſing with his Providence which we ought to maintain; and ſo an <hi>imaginary wrath</hi> in God begets a <hi>real rage</hi> in our peeviſh and inpotent minds. When as indeed the nature of God is as free from <hi>Anger, Hatred, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge,</hi> and all the paſſions of our minds, as it is from <hi>Hands,</hi> or <hi>Eyes,</hi> or <hi>Feet,</hi> or any of the Members of our Bodies. <hi>God is good and doth good,</hi> ſaies our <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſal.</hi> 119. 68. <hi>God is Love,</hi> ſaies the beloved Apoſtle again and again, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 8, 16. And there is nothing more certain, than that God would never af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict his Creature, if ſome grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter good were not in view. He envies not his People any of their Eaſe, Peace, Health, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:38039:84"/> or other Enjoyments; but he loves them with a ſtrong and Holy and Wiſe Affection, and therefore will Afflict them in theſe things whether they will or no, that he may beſtow upon them ſome more ſubſtantial good. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to converſe with God in all his Providences, as with <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Goodneſs, Righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Love it ſelf,</hi> and then you will not be weary of his Diſcipline, or peeviſhly affected towards any of his Diſpenſations. We are apt to cry out, <hi>Oh if we were but ſure of the Love of God towards us in all our Afflictions, we could be then content and patient!</hi> Why, go you and poſſeſs your ſouls in patience, and get your Wills reconciled to the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of God, Love him and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in him, and believe in him
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:38039:85"/> though he Afflict you never ſo ſore, and then be aſſured that God loves you: for the Love and good Will of God, is not his giving the Creature, but it is the communication of himſelf, and his Divine Perfections to your Souls.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="149" facs="tcp:38039:85"/>
                     <head>CHAP. III. <hi>A Second Cauſe aſſigned,</hi> viz. <hi>A miſunderſtanding of our true intereſt. This Explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; Where the true intereſt of Souls is Stated, and the Cure preſcribed in reference to this Cauſe of the Diſtemper. A third Cauſe aſſigned,</hi> viz. <hi>The want of a right diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Good and Evil. Where the nature of Good and Evil is Explained, and Direction given how to diſcern them by way of Cure.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <pb n="150" facs="tcp:38039:86"/>
                     <p> 2. ANother Cauſe of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, is, <hi>A miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of our true intereſt.</hi> Alas how are we ſunk into this body! How ſtudious are we, and fond of the accommodations and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies of this animal life! What fears and jealouſies, cares and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances, what watchings, and prayings, and ſtrivings, and all for the peace and welfare of the fleſh! Certainly we judge our main intereſt to lie in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, pleaſuring, accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the body, and not of the ſoul: which wicked apprehenſion, as it deſtroies all true Religion, ſo particularly it breeds the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper that I am ſpeaking of. We are ſtrangely fond of this <hi>Life,</hi> as <hi>miſerable</hi> as it is, and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:38039:86"/> of this <hi>body,</hi> as unſuitable as it is, and therefore are we ſo much offended with all things that are grievous and hurtful to the ſame; yea we are apt to fret againſt God himſelf, if he do not pleaſe and pamper them as much as we. It is a woful degeneracy that hath befallen the ſoul of man, which makes him miſ-judge and miſtake his main intereſt; the like mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake is not to be found in the whole World ſure. I will not ſay with the Prophet, <hi>Paſs ye over the Iſles of Chittim, and ſend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Kedar, and ſee if there be ſuch a thing;</hi> but indeed paſs ye through the whole Creation, and viſit all the particular beings that are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and you ſhall not find ſuch a thing; ſuch a degeneracy as this is: you ſhall not find any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that thus forgets it ſelf, or
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:38039:87"/> thus miſtakes its main inteteſt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſame be no intereſt, in compariſon of the concernment of an immortal ſoul. Be aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, O ye Heavens, at this mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous abſurdity! The Fig-tree in <hi>Jonathan</hi>'s Parable would not leave its ſweetneſs, to go to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted over the Trees; but this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble plant of the Lord's planting, the rational ſoul, hath forſaken its intereſt and forgotten its proper ſweetneſs, and renounced its own pleaſure and felicity, to go <hi>ſerve its own ſervant,</hi> and ſtudy the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of fleſh and blood: To the ſervice whereof it is ſo entirely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted, that God himſelf muſt be quarrelled with, if he uſe not this <hi>Dalilah</hi> kindly, if he offer to put it to any pain.</p>
                     <p>Be adviſed, I beſeech you, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to <hi>get a right underſtanding</hi>
                        <pb n="153" facs="tcp:38039:87"/> 
                        <hi>of your grand intereſt, and where it lies,</hi> in order to the healing of this diſtemper. Value your ſelves by your ſouls and not by your bodies, by your ſpiritual and not by your corporal ſtate. Is that man happy, whoſe body and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily concernments are all in a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and flouriſhing ſtate, when in the mean time his ſoul is defiled, depraved, deformed, impoveriſhed, and become more vile than the Dung upon the earth, and more wretched than the Beaſts that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh? How then can that man be judged miſerable, whoſe nobler part is beautiful, healthful, rich, and proſperous, although his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and temporal eſtate be ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid, ſordid, contemptible, and much afflicted? Our Saviour hath fully reſolved this Queſtion in the perſons of <hi>Dives</hi> and <hi>Lazarus,</hi>
                        <pb n="154" facs="tcp:38039:88"/> 
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. Live like ſouls, as much as may be, abſtracted from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, provide, take care for, view and viſit your ſouls, value your ſelves happy or unhappy, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as it fares with your ſouls; and then you will find it more na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and eaſie for you to bear up patiently and chearfully under all the Storms that light upon your out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man.</p>
                     <p>3. <hi>The want of a right diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Good and Evil.</hi> This is ſomewhat akin to the former. Our ſouls are ſo ſadly ſunk into mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſo fondly inamoured of our bodies, that we are ready to judge of all things to be good or bad according as they accommodate or incommodate them; and ſo we come many times to put <hi>bitter for ſweet,</hi> and <hi>ſweet for bitter,</hi> Iſa. 5. 20. This is certainly a proper
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:38039:88"/> and immediate cauſe of our flying from, groaning under, and haſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of Afflictions and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, becauſe we judge them hurtful and evil to us. And why evil? Forſooth becauſe they gall our backs, offend our ſenſes, pinch and oppreſs our fleſh. And is this indeed a right rule whereby to judge of the goodneſs or evilneſs of things? Nay, but if you would indeed poſſeſs your ſouls in pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the midſt of bodily preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, then exerciſe your ſpiritual ſenſes to <hi>diſcern</hi> aright <hi>between Good and Evil,</hi> as the Apoſtle's phraſe is, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. <hi>ult.</hi> But how ſhall we thus diſcern; by what rule ſhall we judge them? Good is the rule whereby to judge of Evil, <hi>Rectum eſt Index obliqui:</hi> and then for created good, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God the ſupreme good is
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:38039:89"/> the rule whereby to judge of that; <hi>Perfectum in ſuo genere eſt menſur a reliquorum.</hi> So then judge of all things by their relation that they bear to the nature of God, and the tendency that they have to make us partakers of it. And if we thus judge ſincerely, we ſhall not be ſo much offended at thoſe Providences that are forming us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a reſemblance of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> nor be ſo haſty to run out of that Furnace that is refining us to be <hi>Veſſels of Honour</hi> fit for our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters uſe. If <hi>David</hi> had at this time judged as diſcreetly, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned as clearly, as afterwards he did, he would rather have wiſht for the <hi>ſtrength of an Ox</hi> to <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure,</hi> than the <hi>wings of a Dove</hi> to <hi>eſcape</hi> theſe preſſures; for in the up ſhot of all, when he had viewed and compared all together, and well
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:38039:89"/> recollected himſelf, he profeſſed openly that he accounted it good for him that he met with ſuch uſage in the World, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 67, 71, 75. God is the ſupreme good; that is good for us that brings us nigh and makes us like unto him: and that is not only Proſperity (though indeed that ought to do it, and I hope often doth it) but even Adverſity alſo, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 10. <hi>He chaſteneth us for our profit, that we might be made partakers of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="158" facs="tcp:38039:90"/>
                     <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>The Fourth and laſt Cauſe aſſigned,</hi> viz. <hi>Selfiſhneſs. Self-love brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touch'd upon. Self-will more largely deſcribed, with an earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt advice to bend all our powers againſt this rebellious Giant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THeſe Cauſes of this Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per are to be found in the underſtanding.</p>
                     <p>The Fourth and laſt Cauſe that I ſhall name is in the Will, and
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:38039:90"/> it is <hi>Selfiſhneſs.</hi> By this I mean two things, <hi>Self-love,</hi> and <hi>Self-will.</hi> By Self-love, in this place, I mean ſenſuality, or a <hi>judging of things by ſenſe,</hi> which I have touched upon already; and an <hi>over high valuation of this meer earthly life, and the conveniencies thereof.</hi> Why are we ſo weary of Sickneſs, and ſo impatient under Perſecution? Will it not come to this at length, becauſe we are ſo afraid to die. There can be no farther end of the greateſt Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in this World, than the parting of ſoul and body: Is not this the worſt that can come? It ſeems then that it is an immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate love of this wretched life that is the root of all theſe bitter fears and paſſions.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Labour therefore to be Crucified to the love of this natural life.</hi>
                        <pb n="160" facs="tcp:38039:91"/> There are many inconveniencies and miſeries that do ariſe from this root, which I cannot now name; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly this diſtemper which I am ſpeaking of is a very great one: For however you find <hi>David</hi> here la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring under it, yet elſewhere we find him earneſtly labouring to be rid of it, <hi>Why art thou caſt down, O my ſoul, and why art thou diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted within me,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42. 5, 12. 43. 5. He is troubled at his being troubled, and cannot with patience think how impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent he had been. Strike therefore at the root of this Diſtemper, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to get your over-fond love and over-high valuation of this earthly life mortified. He will be able not only to endure, but even to contemn all Adverſity, who hath once well learnt to contemn his own life. He cannot be in the
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:38039:91"/> power of any who hath death in his own power, ſaies <hi>Seneca:</hi> which admits of a good ſenſe and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to our Chriſtian Divinity, though he did not mean it ſo.</p>
                     <p>The other branch of ſelfiſhneſs is <hi>Self-will:</hi> And this alſo is a peſtilent diſturber of the mind, and engages the ſoul in many quarrels againſt God. The underſtanding indeed may be miſtaken, and the fleſh may ſmart, and the Devil may tempt, but I think the proud, petulant, perverſe Self-will is the <hi>Achan;</hi> the grand troubler of the ſoul: This is the Sea from whence ariſe all thoſe Clouds and Storms that trouble the Earth and infeſt Heaven it ſelf. If this were tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly mortified, I dare ſay all the skill of earth, all the Magick of Hell, all the paſſions and pangs of the body could not make a cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:38039:92"/> ſoul. This was the cauſe of <hi>Jonah</hi>'s heat and rage, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of death, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe he might not have his own will. Yea, and it ſeems that <hi>Job</hi>'s will was not molded into the Will of God, and that that was the cauſe of his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience; for his complaint is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a contending with the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that by <hi>Job</hi> himſelf, <hi>Job.</hi> 40. 2.</p>
                     <p>I do earneſtly adviſe you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to bend all your ſtrength againſt this rebellious Giant, and be daily begging more ſtrength than yet you have. If you can overcome your own Wills, you need not fear being overcome by any Adverſity: He that can deny himſelf, can do any thing. The Will of God is holy, pure and perfect, and indeed it is not only the duty, but the glory of man to comply with it freely and
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:38039:92"/> chearfully. What can be more Divine than a will according to God's Will, an Heart according to God's Heart? It was the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of <hi>David</hi> you know, yea it is the perfection of Angels. I have often obſerved with great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light the excellent patience, and compoſure of <hi>David</hi>'s ſpirit in the time of his flight from <hi>Abſalom,</hi> which you will find recorded in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15, and 16 Chap. and you may ſee that he poſſeſt his ſoul in ſo much patience by this means, by eying the abſolute goodneſs of the Will of God, and reſigning him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf thereunto, Chap. 15. 26. and Chap. 16. 10. The patience of our Lord and Saviour was much more admirable than his; and he was a perſon whoſe will was ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in the Will of God, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. 42. <hi>Not my will but thy Will be</hi>
                        <pb n="164" facs="tcp:38039:93"/> 
                        <hi>done.</hi> The time and matter, and manner, and meaſure of all your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are all ordered by a Will and Wiſdom which is above, that is infinitely pure and perfect: O there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore labour to get your wills recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to this Divine Will, and your hearts at all times overpowered and maſtered with the ſenſe of the infinite goodneſs and holineſs thereof; and ſo ſhall you find all wrath and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, all diſcontents and jealouſies to die and wither away, and you will poſſeſs your ſouls in peace and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in patience and ſerenity, in the midſt of all your Afflictions.</p>
                     <p>I know ſeveral other cauſes might be brought of this diſtemper; but I conceive they are either ſuch as are inferiour and leſs principal; or ſuch as may be reduced to ſome of theſe that I have aſſigned. Therefore I paſs on to the Improvement.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="165" facs="tcp:38039:93"/>
                     <head>CHAP. V. <hi>The Improvement, by way of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, that there is an averſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the humane nature from Afflictions which is purely na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural: How it becomes ſinful. Secondly, It is a greater diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per when unlawful means are uſed for deliverance out of Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity. Thirdly, An Exhortation to beware of this Diſeaſe, and to labour after a contrary tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Which temper recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in three things. Firſt, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience under the troubles of</hi>
                        <pb n="166" facs="tcp:38039:94"/> 
                        <hi>this life. This preſſed with two or three weighty conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Secondly, Wearineſs of the Imperfections of life. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Eager deſires of Eternal reſt. How to turn</hi> David's <hi>Rhetorick into Divinity.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AND here I will grant, that there is an averſeneſs in the humane nature from Afflictions, and a deſire of releaſe from them, which is purely natural, which is not properly ſinful as I conceive, no more than eating, or drinking, or ſleeping is. But it eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ſinful many waies; when it is not rightly ordered, directed and bounded by our wills, or when our wills do concur with the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderlineſs and exceſs of it: And
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:38039:94"/> ſo it is when the averſeneſs of the nature becomes impatience in the will, and deſires in the appetite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come turbulent paſſions in the higher powers of the Soul.</p>
                     <p>2. If impatience of troubles, and eager deſires of reſt from Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity be a Diſtemper, then much worſe is it when unlawful and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct means and courſes are added thereunto: <hi>David</hi> indeed was ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, over eager of deliverance; yet we do not find that he uſed unlawful waies to decline the rage of <hi>Saul,</hi> and to ſave his life, but he conſulted with God and pray'd unto him, and ſo ſtood upon his own defence. The wings of a <hi>Dove</hi> are ſwift indeed, but they are honeſt and innocent. But what ſhall we ſay to them that take to themſelves wings to eſcape, and that the wings of a <hi>Hawk</hi> or a
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:38039:95"/> 
                        <hi>Vulture,</hi> that deliver themſelves by Injuſtice, Rapine, Murder and Deceit, that break the Snare by breaking Vows, and Oaths, and Promiſes; that care not if they ſwim through a Sea of Blood, ſo they may but get ſafe to Land; that to redeem their bodies will not ſtick to ſacrifice their ſouls. <hi>David</hi>'s indeed was a great diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, but this is a deſperate and Deviliſh madneſs.</p>
                     <p>But that which I do principally infer, and moſt of all preſs from the conſideration of <hi>David</hi>'s di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, is, that you would dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently endeavour to beware of the like: The infirmities of Saints are not recorded for our imitation, no nor to afford us a way of excuſing our ſelves, but indeed for our cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and they will render us the more inexcuſable, if we beware
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:38039:95"/> not that whereof we are ſo warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Now that you may be ſafe and ſound from this diſtemper, labour to get a contrary temper. Three things therefore I exhort you to in oppoſition to this diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, to wit, <hi>Patience under trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of this life, Impatience of the imperfections of this life, and eager deſires of eternal reſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. Labour to be patient and during of the troubles of this life, and moderate your deſires of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance and reſt from Adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Think not <hi>much,</hi> nor think not <hi>long</hi> concerning any tryal, as if ſome <hi>ſtrange</hi> thing, or ſome <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal</hi> thing befell you: Labour to be mortified (as much as may be) to the ſenſe of all bodily Afflictions, and moderated in the expectations of temporal delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, in as much as the former
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:38039:96"/> is not properly your miſery, nor can the latter of it ſelf be your happineſs. What an unſeemly thing is it to hear Chriſtians vent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their paſſions, ſpending all their complaints upon their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtate, Oppreſſions, Injuries, Perſecutions, and ſpending all their Prayers upon their fleſhly intereſt, as if it were by that that they muſt live and be happy. Oh that the voice of this weeping might be heard no more amongſt us! Was it not a childiſh thing in the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to weep and whine after a little fleſh? Do but read the ſtory in <hi>Numb.</hi> 11. 4, 5, 6. and you will take it rather to be the puling of Children, than the complaint of men, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the men of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Wherein was the cry of the men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> after Corn, and other ſenſual ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations,
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:38039:96"/> better than the howling of Dogs; to which it ſeems to be compared, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7. 14. Concerning this impatience of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and eagerneſs after relief and eaſe, and reſt; I need not ſay as our Saviour ſaies, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. <hi>Do not even the Publicans the ſame;</hi> but do not even the <hi>Beaſts</hi> the ſame? do not they groan under their burden? do not they long to be delivered from their pains and preſſures, and reſtraints? And ſhall the longing of ſouls be no higher nor purer than thoſe of a meer animal appetite? Shall the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Sons of God be of no higher a ſtrain than the Children of the Raven, which are ſaid to cry unto God <hi>for meat, Job</hi> 38. <hi>ult.</hi> Set aſide the elegancy of them, and all your groanings under Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and luſting after deliverance,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:38039:97"/> are common to the beaſts that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh as well as you. And this may well be the firſt Motive to the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which I exhort you to.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Conſider that if you be thus weary of Affliction, and eager af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reſt, you do<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſecretly find fault with a chief piece of God's diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations in the World, and fruſtrate the ends which God hath in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tribulation upon the righteous. The exerciſe of Graces, ſuch as Patience, Self-denial, Faithfulneſs, Courage, Conſtancy is the great end of God in all his afflictive Providences upon his people: and if we be ſo ſoon weary of them, and ſo importunately bent upon deliverance from them, how can this great deſign of Heaven be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled? For can the Plaiſter work a Cure except it may be ſuffered to lie on?</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <pb n="173" facs="tcp:38039:97"/> 3. Conſider that there is really more valour and true greatneſs of mind in enduring hardſhips pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently and conſtantly, than in all theſe fightings and contendings for God, which paſs with many men for ſuch a noble zeal. <hi>To dare to live</hi> in an unpleaſant and bitter time, is much more magnanimous than <hi>to wiſh to die;</hi> and to endure the anguiſhes of life with an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble patience and ſubmiſſive ſpirit, is more Divine than to endeavour to eſcape them. This paſſive va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour was the mighty courage of the Son of God, whereby he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came all that was againſt him. How eaſie was it for him to have revenged himſelf upon all his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, by Legions of Angels, or Fire from Heaven? How eaſily could he have frown'd them all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their firſt nothing? But he gave
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:38039:98"/> his back to the ſmiter, and his cheeks to them that pull'd off the hair; he was dumb as a Sheep be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Shearers: whereby he gave us an Example of the moſt admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>longanimity</hi> and <hi>magnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> too; and by enduring the Croſs did perfectly vanquiſh all that Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified him. We do mightily ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the valiant Acts of <hi>David</hi>'s Worthies, when we read how one ſlew eight hundred at one time; another reſiſted the whole Army of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and ſlew many of them; another defended a piece of Ground from a whole Troop of <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and ſlew them; another ſlew a Lion and two Lion-like men; another went down to an <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> Champion only with a Staff, and firſt ſpoil'd the <hi>Egyptian</hi> of his Spear, and then ſlew him with it. I will not diſparage this valour of
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:38039:98"/> theirs; but I will affirm that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> in his flight from <hi>Abſalom</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted a more excellent courage, than when he ſlew the great <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtine;</hi> and that the valour of theſe his Worthies in it ſelf conſidered, is no more to be compared to the admirable Patience, Self-denial and ſubmiſſion of the <hi>Redeemer</hi> of the World, or to that of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was but one of his ſervants, than the paſſions of a Beaſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e to be compared unto the ingenuous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of a rational ſoul. For ſuch a kind of animal courage, fierceneſs and killing faculty, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Beaſts of the Earth have as much, <hi>Adino, Eleazar, Shanimah,</hi> or <hi>Benaiah</hi> the ſon of <hi>Jehojadah,</hi> ſo much commended in the 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. True valour conſiſts not in the greatneſs of bones, but in the greatneſs of mind, not
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:38039:99"/> in ſtrength of ſinews but in ſtrength of Grace, not in the fierceneſs and ſightingneſs, but in the meekneſs and patience of diſpoſition. That's not the true generouſneſs of ſpirit which cannot brook injuries; but indeed that which can: That's not the true valiant mind which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, what ever comes of it, to have its own will; but that which moſt freely reſigns it ſelf to the Will of God. <hi>Quo minus quid ſibi arrogat homo, eò evadit nobilior &amp; divinior.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>2. Inſtead of being weary of the Perſecutions of life, be ye weary of the imperfections of life: Let the <hi>body of death,</hi> rather than <hi>the troubles of God,</hi> be the cauſe of your wearineſs and complaint, <hi>O wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man,</hi> &amp;c. It is valour to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure patiently the Afflictions of the body; but to mourn under the
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:38039:99"/> infirm and imperfect condition of the ſoul, whilſt it is embodied, is alſo devout and pious: yea to be content to ſpend an Eternity in ſuch an imperfect ſtate, and ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitable body as this, were an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of a mind over ſluggiſh and forgetful of its own bliſs. And yet I cannot ſay, but that there is ſomething of Religion in the ſouls patient induring of its imperfect condition in the body, becauſe the Will of God is ſo.</p>
                     <p>3. Convert the animal appetites into Divine longings; inſtead of eagerneſs of reſt from Adverſity, be as eager as may be of Eternal Reſt, of a ſtate of perfection and glory. Let not the Beaſt be above the Man, the ſenſual appetite be ſtronger than the ſpiritual, let not <hi>David</hi>'s thirſting after the waters of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.) nor
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:38039:100"/> the <hi>Bond-ſervant</hi> panting after the ſhadow <hi>(Job</hi> 7. 2.) condemn your lazy ſouls that have a more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable object ſet before them. It is good to be a Horſe-Leech here; ſuck in what you can of Eternal Life, and after all yet cry, <hi>Give, give.</hi> In a word then, to turn <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>Rhetorick</hi> into <hi>Divinity;</hi> Inſtead of, <hi>Oh that I had wings like a Dove,</hi> cry ye, Oh that I had the <hi>Heart of Dove,</hi> chaſtly adhering to God, innocently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>having it ſelf towards men, and patiently enduring injuries! In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of, Oh that he would give me wings like a Dove, that I might <hi>flye away,</hi> pray ye, Oh that one would give me the wings of Faith and Hope, that I might <hi>ſoar aloft</hi> in a diſdain of Worldly Evils! The <hi>wings of the Oſtrich that lifteth up her ſelf on high, and</hi>
                        <pb n="179" facs="tcp:38039:100"/> 
                        <hi>ſcorneth the Horſe and his Rider!</hi> Inſtead of the wings of a Dove to flye away and <hi>be at reſt,</hi> wiſh rather, Oh that one would give me the wings of an <hi>Eagle,</hi> that I might <hi>flye away towards Heaven!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
